<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The spirituall armour With which being furnished, a Christian may be able to stand fast in the euill day, and time of tryall; and to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. Written by that godly and learned man, Paul Baine; sometime Preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 160 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851986</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851986</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1126:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The spirituall armour With which being furnished, a Christian may be able to stand fast in the euill day, and time of tryall; and to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked. Written by that godly and learned man, Paul Baine; sometime Preacher of Gods word at S. Andrewes in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 313, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for R. Milbourn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17283:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17283:1"/>
            <p>THE SPIRITVALL ARMOVR.</p>
            <p>With which being furniſhed, a Chriſtian may be able to ſtand <hi>faſt in the euill day, and time of tryall; and to quench all</hi> the fiery Darts of the wicked.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by that godly and learned man,</hi> PAVL BAINE; <hi>ſometime Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Gods word at</hi> S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes <hi>in</hi> Cambridge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. L.</hi> for <hi>R. Milbourn.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17283:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17283:2"/>
            <head>To the godly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader) hath left this world, and is gone to the place of the bleſſed, reſting himſelfe in the boſom of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Abraham.</hi> Hee vvas a godly and faithfull man whileſt hee liued, as his life ſhewed; ſo alſo his labours and workes which hee hath
<pb facs="tcp:17283:3"/> left behinde him doe teſtifie. Pittie it is his dayes were no longer, that hee might haue finiſhed many things him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe which hee had begun; ſome of which are perfected by others, and ſome likely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to come forth. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it fare with other of his Works, it ſeemeth that this was perfected in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, by his owne hands; which I wiſh may not onely come to the hands of Gods children, but into their hearts chiefly. And though he haue finiſhed his courſe &amp; is gone the way of all fleſh; yet think that hee ſpeaketh to thee by this Book, &amp; bids thee to put
<pb facs="tcp:17283:3"/> on this <hi>ſpirituall Armour,</hi> which is indeede the whole Armor of God. For this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour being put on will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thy ſoule against not ſome, but all the fiery darts of the wicked. Happy &amp; thrice happy is that ſoule that is thus defended: for it ſhall go well with it heere in this world; but a thouſand times better with it in the world to come. Reade it: remember it: practiſe it: and the Lord giue thee vnderstanding in all things: and bleſſe it vnto thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17283:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17283:4"/>
            <head>THE SPIRITVALL <hi>Armour.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES. 6.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Finally, my brethren, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followes the concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Epiſtle: in which are three things; firſt, an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the 21. verſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, a narration of diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching <hi>Tychicus,</hi> verſ. 21.22.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17283:5"/> Thirdly, a farewel, verſe 23.24.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is, that wee would fortifie our ſelues, to the end wee may goe through with theſe things which oppoſe vs in our Chriſtian warfare.</p>
            <p>Now the manner is two-folde: Firſt, by looking at the ſtrength we haue out of our ſelues in God, Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, by harneſſing our ſelues with a ſpirituall ſtrength in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in vs. For theſe do not one explane the other, becauſe 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, Gods ſtrength and faith are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, as the matter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and the hand apprehending; and it is more ſutable to this Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory: For the ſtrength of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17283:5"/> the common ſouldiers is as much, yea farre more in the wiſedome &amp; power of their Leader, then in their owne valour and furniture. But one may ſay, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Why doth hee ſay <hi>in the power of his might,</hi> and not <hi>in the Lord</hi> onely. <hi>Anſwer:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The firſt is a more generall obiect of our faith <hi>[in the Lord]</hi> in his wiſdom, mercy, faithfulneſſe, (for all theſe doe ſtrengthen vs). The other is that immediat thing in which is all our helpe, as keeping vs to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Now that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hauing exhorted to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and godly life, doth ſtrike vp a Drum, and ſound an alarm; it doth giue vs to vnderſtand, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>the practice of good duties hath no ſmall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17283:6"/> against them.</hi> The Diuel wil ſoon (if we ſet our ſelues this waies) cry for clubs, &amp; reach vs ſome knocks. Wee ſhall know that theſe things ſhall coſt vs the ſetting on. Thus in Chriſt when he ſet vpon the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, Satan did tempt him, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 4. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.21. when he would doe good, euill would ſtirre in him: and when <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.18. did purpoſe to come &amp; viſit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their faith, Satan did hinder him: and <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.46. when Chriſt was fruitfully teaching, there we ſee his acquaintance at the doore to ſpeake with him, calling him from the worke in hand, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.22.23.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17283:6"/> when hee tolde them of his ſuffering, Satan by <hi>Peter</hi> ſought to turn him from it (Saue thy ſelf). O ſuch is the force of Satans oppoſition, that a man when once hee ſetteth him ſelfe to this or that good thing earneſtly, he is beaten from it farther then before: euen as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were who are types to vs; when they turned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to forſake Egypt, their ſeruitude was redoubled. <hi>Exod.</hi> 5. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> They therefore muſt teach vs not to count it ſtrange when we find ſuch difficulties in the wayes which are good: for when a man doth looke to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, he doth then leaue the kingdome of darkneſſe, and the tyrant cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17283:7"/> this with patience. As at other tryals ſo at this we muſt not wonder. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Dearly beloued thinke it not ſtrange concerning the fiery triall,</hi> Why ſhould we think that ſo ſtrange which is ſo frequent, as our meat is not more vſual? When we wold buckle to ſome more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall duties, then ſuch an ill diſpoſition commeth vpon vs: euill is preſent, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell doth make vs to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyed with ſwarms of idle thoughts: then what neede wee vſe ſuch ſtrictneſſe? bee good to your ſelfe, then this friend wold ſpeak with vs, this buſineſſe is vndone, this matter lieth in deſpaire, thy mother is at the doore, then we are moyled &amp; dee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17283:7"/> often in the ſin wee fled from, then before. While I was muſing, the fire brake forth, then ſpake I with my tongue, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 39.3. Wee muſt not think this ſtrange; but though we be beaten on our knees, yet goe ſtill from Egypt the kingdom of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the glorious inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the Saints in light.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2. This doth ſhew ſuch whoſe courſe is cleare and euen, goe ſmoothly away with all their enterpriſes, that they are taken of the Diuell to doe his will: for it they did not pleaſe him, then hee would haue a ſaying to them. <hi>Now particularly in this verſ. two things muſt be opened.</hi> 1. <hi>That Chriſtians muſt haue a reſolution in their courſes. Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17283:8"/> who it is or vpon what ſtrength it is wee must be cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageous.</hi> For the firſt, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth ſo much, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Watch yee, ſtand faſt, quite your ſelues like men:</hi> hee doth call vpon vs to bee valorous, like as <hi>Ioab</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſouldiers fighting for their countrey, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.12. And of the Chriſtians, it is ſaide, they did with full purpoſe of heart cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord: and the ſelfe ſame ſpirituall fortitude is neceſſary in the things wee vndertake or ſuffer, if wee meane to goe through with them.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.10.</note> Take heed therefore: for the Lord hath choſen thee to build the houſe of his Sanctuary, be ſtrong therefore &amp; do it. <hi>Luk</hi> 9.51.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17283:8"/> It is ſayde of our Sauiour Chriſt when his time was come to ſuffer, hee ſet him ſelfe fully to goe to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. <hi>Now this ſpirituall cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage doth ſhew it ſelfe in three things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it doth <hi>expell the fears of cowardiſe, when we ſee great enemies againſt vs. Deut.</hi> 20.23. Let not your hearts feare nor be afraide of them: for though a man ſee a hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maſſe of corruption, yet ſhall it not affright him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>It makes vs not to be diſmaide at the difficulties that meete with vs:</hi> though a man come by knocks, yet hee maketh not dainties of them. For <hi>Paul</hi> though hee was driuen vpon that he would not, yet he was not diſmaid, but gaue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17283:9"/> God thankes that the beſt part of him did looke ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, &amp; that Chriſt was his righteouſnes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. It doth ſhew it ſelfe in this, that <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we are foyled, it maketh vs renew our battell,</hi> and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly charge our enemies with freſh aſſaults. <hi>Iud.</hi> 20.22. The men of Iſrael pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp their hearts (there is courage) and renewed the battell; ſo <hi>Paul,</hi> though the Diuell did buffet him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and againe, yet being courageous, hee did renew his ſtrength againſt it by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prayer. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This then doth rebuke the timorouſneſſe in vs, that when wee ſee the manifolde enemies, which we haue, our hearts melt, &amp; if we be foyled, are ready to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17283:9"/> caſt away our weapons; which cowardiſe doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the aduerſary, as courage doth daunt him. The Diuell is like a ſerpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Crocodile: the property of which is, if one follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, it flieth away; if one fly, it purſueth him: reſiſt him, he ſhall fly; be afraid, he wil follow. Men are, as <hi>Ieremy</hi> complaineth, courageous to doe euill, but they haue no courage to doe good. If a Bear or Lion be in the way, they will encounter the greateſt difficulties: if one courſe proue not, they will turne euery ſtone; which ſhould make vs much more double our courage in that which is good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wee ſee hence, how
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17283:10"/> that Gods almighty ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth is it, on which our courage muſt be builded. <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.15 Thus ſaith the Lord God, in quietneſs and reſt ſhall ye be ſaued, in quietneſſe and confidence ſhall bee your ſtrength, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.14. I can do al things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth mee. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. We are kept by the power of God vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for no ſtrength but his can preuaile againſt the ſtrong one in the world: he bruſeth the Serpents head, he diſſolueth the workes of Satan, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 3.8. The Iſraelites could not haue come out of Egypt, nor entred the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naean,</hi> if the Lord had not ſubdued their enemies, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17283:10"/> might they bee confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in ſword or bowe, but in the name of the Lord on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in their ſtrong God: much more muſt our cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage be builded on God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their enemies are fleſh, ours are ſpirits of great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Look as it is in ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, their chiefeſt ſtrength li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in their Captain: ſo is it true heer, that al our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth lieth in Chriſt, the Captaine that leadeth vs to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his power doth all our workes for vs: &amp; that which is to be in vs, doth but fit vs to ſtand ſtil and look to this almighty power of God, which ſubdueth all things for vs. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> It muſt teach vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to diſclaime our owne ſtrength: he rhat will be wiſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17283:11"/> muſt become a fool; he that wil be ſtrong, muſt learn to ſee himſelf to be weaknes it ſelfe. Wee our ſelues before our conuerſion are of no ſtrength. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6. After, of no ſtrength: Not that we are ſufficient to thinke a good thought. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. None can name the Lord Ieſus, but by the holy Ghoſt. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3. Hee is happy that is grown vp to be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of himſelfe: we are as full of ſelfe-confidence as of ſelf-loue, though we cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it. This is the reaſon wee are ſo often foyled, that wee might ſee wee are of no ſtrength, that all our vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories muſt com from G d. <hi>Iud.</hi> 20. The Lord let the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralites fal in a moſt iuſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17283:11"/> againſt their brethren, that hee might ſtrip them of that ſelf confident preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had in themſelues. And <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo holy an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, was brought to the gates of death that he might learne this leſſon. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.9. What maketh vs after diuers fals, to bee no more afraid of the enemies that buffet vs? what maketh vs that we can no more feelingly run vnder the wings of Chriſt? whence is it that we haue no more pouerty of ſpirit in the evperience of our frailties, but that ſecret ſelfe-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is mighty in vs? Seeing that all our courage muſt be in this, that God is with vs; let vs bee nothing in our ſelues. The bleſſed ſoules can
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17283:12"/> ſay with <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.3. We are thoſe whoſe harts being circumciſed, reioyce in the Lord Ieſus, and haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, let vs learne to build our ſelues on this Rock, on our ſtrong God Chriſt Ieſus. As thoſe vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <hi>Philiſtims</hi> did place all their hopes of the battell in their <hi>Goliah:</hi> ſo muſt wee place all our hope in Chriſt Ieſus: this is our ſtrength, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſtill, fear not, behold the ſaluation of the Lord which he will ſhew to you this day. <hi>This is a moſt bleſſed estate, to leane on the Lord, and on the power of his might: many are the benefits of it.</hi> It will feare no oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition. For what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not Gods
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17283:12"/> almighty power ſubdue? <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 27.1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It will not be diſmaid when all meanes in ordinary conſideration faile vs: hee ſaueth by few, yea without any, as well as many. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Abraham</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not for the deadneſſe of his body. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Hee that hath no truſt in himſelfe, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth on the power of God, will, though he fall often, ſtil haue hope: for hee that knowes he hath no ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not wonder if when God leaueth him hee doe fall: and hee that maketh Gods ſtrength his ſtay, though he be neuer ſo far from a thing, yet will not caſt away hope in time to obtaine. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Finally, hee will deſire to grieue ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lently for his weakneſſe, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17283:13"/> will ſo learne to ſee there is no ability in him, that hee will further leane his faith on the power of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.11. Giue vs help againſt trouble, for vaine is the help of man. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.29. When I am poor and in heauineſs, thy helpe O Lord. ſhall ſtill exalt me. What vſe the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> maketh of this, that the Iſraelites had fought vnſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfully as left of God? Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> this is all our ſecurity, that it is not the ſtrength in vs, but the power of Gods might that muſt helpe vs to ſaluation. If wee had the ſtrength of our firſt parents, and were left to our ſelues, wee ſhould come ſhort of happineſſe: but this being it that doth keepe vs (Gods
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17283:13"/> ſtrength being truſted to by faith) the ſelfe ſame ſtrong God being the author and finiſher of our faith. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. this puts all out of doubt. 3. We muſt glorifie the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God in all things; it is he that ſtrengtheneth vs. <hi>Eſay</hi> 25.10. He worketh all our works for vs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108.13. Throgh him we ſhal do valiantly, hee is our ſhield, tower, rock, ſtrength, and glory.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of fortifying, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the furniture we are to haue; laid downe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to the 14. verſe, in particular to the 21. Firſt, he layeth downe the dutie. Secondly, he doth, as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Herald, againe repeate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17283:14"/> his proclamation, becauſe we cannot heare on this ſide eaſily, but would ſaue our ſelues peaceably, without looking after warfare. In lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe the dutie, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth in the beginning of this verſe, the thing to bee done: Put on the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God. 2. The end, that you may be able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. 3. The reaſon, which hath reference to the dutie, and end; in the 12. verſe. Now in the thing to bee done, three things are to be marked. 1. That Chriſtians muſt haue armour that is compleate armour, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them from top to toe. 2. That they muſt not haue it lying by them, but muſt put it on. 3. That the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17283:14"/> armour is for matter and making, of God, that is, divine and ſpirituall. For the firſt, <hi>there is great reaſon to proue that a Christian muſt haue armour.</hi> For he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies that would wound him deadly otherwiſe: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>1</label> It is with vs as with the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites in <hi>Exodus:</hi> ſo ſoone as hee tooke them out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, hee led them thence armed; becauſe that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> hee knew would followe them, and puiſſant Kings encounter them as they marched to their inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, a Chriſtian is borne with his armor on his back, ſo that he can as wel ceaſe to be a Chriſtian as ceaſe to be armed. That which is fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſpoken of the race of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17283:15"/> Gyants, is truely ſpoken of vs; we are no ſooner born then wee haue our ſwords girded to vs, our ſhields on our arms, &amp;c. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> For the word doth beget vs, Faith is the firſt thing formed in vs. <hi>Now that wee muſt haue compleate armour, it is hence manifeſt:</hi> becauſe it were in vaine to haue ſome parts couered, and to lie open to mortall wounds in other ſome. The Diuell is like thoſe Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, who if they cannot wound the head nor the heart, they will prick any part rather then faile. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians then muſt haue their compleat harneſſe couering them from top to toe, which doth ſhew vs how vnchriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many are, who know not if
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17283:15"/> they ſhould ſpeak truth that that there is any ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Like Iſrael when there was not a Smith, nor a weapon in it: ſo is the face of our Iſraelites, they look not (though they haue bound themſelues by the Sacrament to be warriours) after armour. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> If thou haſt not this armour, knowe the Diuell hath ſurpriſed thee, and holdeth thee as a ſlaue to him. Againe, many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that they muſt haue com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleate armour, ſuch as muſt couer them all ouer: and therefore though in ſome things they ſeeme couered, yet in others they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out defence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt mark that he doth not ſay, we muſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17283:16"/> have armour, or prepare it, but we muſt put it on: ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thence, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to knowe there is ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, but we muſt haue it buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled alwaies vpon vs, in readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by vs:</hi> we muſt not doe as many, who haue ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robes of apparell, but they weare them not; as good haue none, as vſe it not. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But you will ask me, How may we put it on? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If we do vncaſe vs of that which will not let it bee drawne vpon vs: for as he which vvould put on a nevv ſuit, muſt firſt put off his olde; ſo vve. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, vve muſt in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of our infirmity pray to God to fit this furniture about vs: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for, looke as little children, although they have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17283:16"/> apparell, they cannot put it on further then the nurſe or mother doth make them rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: ſo it is vvith vs. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vvee muſt put on theſe things by exciting and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting them: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Wouldeſt thou put on the ſhield of faith? doo it thus; I am a poore captive: vvell, Chriſt hath bid mee hold him, and he vvill make me free. I am troubled vvith lavves of evill: vvell, Chriſt is a ſanctifier: every time vve renevv faith, vve put on this ſhield. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, the vſe of this armour doth put it on: for beſides as in apparell by ſtretching our ſelves vvee make it fall to our bodies, theſe graces have this; being exerciſed, they increaſe the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17283:17"/> more.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> This doth rebuke many, yea many that have armour. Look, as evidences, till ſom flavv be found, are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed: ſo our vveapons, till God muſter vs vvith ſome calamities, are not vſed. When I ſee theſe ruſty hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berds, calivers, muskets, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp in the time of peace, I may ſee hovv it is vvith our ſoules. The graces of God are not kept ſhining, vvee do not gird them daily to vs as vve ought: therefore vvhen vve ſhould vſe them vvee ſhall finde them out of kilture at the leaſt. Againe, many ſlothfull ſouldiers for eaſe put-on ſome, and leave off otherſom: though they look to the maine, yet
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17283:17"/> they care not for the lighter vvounds; their eies, tongues, eares are ſhot through, as <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Vriahs</hi> matter had not his eies fenced.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Againe, it lets vs ſee hovv vvel a multitude of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a virgin betrothed to Chriſt, may be compared to an army (for terrour) vvith banners. Is it not a fearefull thing for an enemy to ſee an army all clad vvith gliſtring armour from the crovvn of the head to the feet? ſo is it for theſe ſpirits to ſee their ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſo armed. The laſt thing to bee marked in the duty, is <hi>the kinde of armour</hi> [of God] <hi>which word noteth</hi> both <hi>the maker and metall of it;</hi> teaching vs, that the vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons vvherevvith vvee reſiſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17283:18"/> the divell muſt be ſpirituall. Our vveapons (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) are not carnall, but ſpirituall, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. <hi>There is no armour of proofe able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him, which God himſelf doth not forge,</hi> and is not ſpiritual: for the ſtrength of braſſe and ſtone is nothing to him; that of the Leviathan may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to him, <hi>Iob.</hi> 41.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch muſt the armour be to reſiſt, as the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault is vvhich is made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a thing: novv the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell doth not come againſt vs vvith ſvvords, but vvith ſpirituall ſuggeſtions to vvithdravv vs; labouring <hi>to withdraw vs</hi> from righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and fellovvſhip vvith God, to vnrighteouſnes and the creature, leaving the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17283:18"/> Wherefore vvee muſt not fence our ſelues againſt the aſſaults of Satan by any human means, by any thing vvhich the vviſdome of man can ſuggeſt: but as <hi>David,</hi> encountring vvith <hi>Goliah,</hi> laid aſide <hi>Saul</hi>'s vveapons &amp; furniture, and vvent againſt him in the Name of the Lord: ſo vvee muſt ſay, Not armed vvith our ovvn vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſtrength, or helps of the creature, do vve ſeek to put to flight the povver of darknes, but in Gods armor vve make reſiſtance. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it doth convince many of notable folly, vvho vvill march againſt the divel with armour fleſhly and diveliſh; as the Papiſts, vvho in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion haue banners vpon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17283:19"/> poles, vvho on Palme-Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day cary palm-boughs, vvho put truſt on croſſes, crucifix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, holy vvater, &amp;c: for, not knovving the power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, they think vvith fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ceremonies to chaſe away the ſpiritual powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Againe, many troubled vvith tentations of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or ſelf-murder, they vvil to phyſick; as if by letting of blood or vomit, they could purge out the divell: others, vvhen the evill ſpirit doth annoy them, they make reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance but as <hi>Saul,</hi> call for muſick, this or that compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and employ themſelues more buſily, that one naile may driue out another; in a vvord, ſo reſiſting that evill one, troubling themſelves,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17283:19"/> that they make themſelues twofolde more the children of the Diuell. 4. There are ſome who when they are ſo troubled, will not ſticke to goe to wiſards: when the Diuell doth wound them, they will ſeeke to him for a plaiſter: that cure will bee well done, when the murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpirit muſt play the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon. Now followeth the end, <hi>that yee may bee able to ſtand.</hi> Two things muſt bee vnfolded. 1. What this meanes <hi>(to ſtand)? Anſ. A ſouldier ſtanding orderly to his fight, doth neither run forth to his perill, nor retyre through cowardiſe; neither is beaten downe through violence.</hi> So that <hi>ſtanding,</hi> is holding their courſe without hurt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17283:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſſaults of the Diuell are of two ſorts:</hi> forcible or poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike. Now this Text ſpeaks of thoſe ſubtle ſtratagems, the worde ſignifying one principall kinde (to witte) ambuſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that put for the other: the ſenſe then of the words is, that you may bee preſerued harmeleſſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Diuell do practice all his ſtratagems a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. Thus you ſee what is the benefite of our Chriſtian furniture: it doth put vs out of danger; this is tryed proofe, we neede not feare any ſhot if it bee well buckled vnto vs: thus Chriſt being with this har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed, the Diuell could not faſten any thing on him: for euen ſome peeces, are of no
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17283:20"/> leſſe force, much more the whole. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. He thay ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth faith, vertue, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (which all is but the breſtplate of righteouſnes) ſhall not fall: <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, faith (which is but our ſhield) is our victory. Now if one peece bee of ſuch vſe, how beneficiall is the whole? Againe, in the falls of the Saints it may be ſeene how they caught their wipes, for lacke of their armor. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Which muſt teach vs firſt, to priſe and get vs this furniture. We ſee how going to warres we eſteeme more then life ſuch an armour as can ſecure vs, that wee need not take care for gunſhot: how much more ſhould wee count of this, which keepeth the life
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17283:21"/> of God from being woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſoule. Which if we were fully clad with, vve might fight at the Cannons mouth ſecure from danger. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. It doth let vs ſee what we muſt blame when wee are wounded; our want to our ſelues in not putting on this armour: for hence it was cauſed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wee ſee that the Diuell doth vſe policie in aſſaying vs,</hi> Thus from the beginning he ſhewed more of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent then of the Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. He did through deceit beguile <hi>Euah.</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. His working is not in all power onely, but in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celuablenes of vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: he is the father of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Machiaueliſme: hee
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17283:21"/> knoweth the Lions skin wil not come where the Foxes may enter; and if hee were ſtrength without ſubtilty, he were the leſſe to be feared. For vvhat is the Poets <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus</hi> vvhen his eyes are vvanting? what is ſtrength if wiſedome and policie bee vvanting or abſent. But for our further inſtruction, wee muſt ſearch out vvhat theſe ſubtill ſtrat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gems are, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvith hee doth circumuent vs: not that vvee can finde them all out, but that wee may point at the fountaines of further meditation.</p>
            <p>Theſe may be conſidered generally, or more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly. Generally, his policy in fight is, that he obſerueth all circumſtances for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17283:22"/> as perſon, place, time; and as hee ſet vpon Chriſt in the Deſart when hee was now hungry: the condition of the party, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in proſperity or in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, religious, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe: his weapon in choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and vſing of which hee ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h great s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill: and two things are here remarkable and moſt eminent. Firſt, that hee will then redouble his forces, when after God is ready to remooue him: as men that beſiege a Citie, if they haue intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of any power comming to remoue their ſiege, they will put forth all their courage: try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if they may make breach or ſcale the walls and enter. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 12.12. Hee can ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17283:22"/> watch opportunity, that he can be ready to hurt vs with our owne weapons. As 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 27. hee would haue ſwallowed vp the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in his repentant ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The more particular conflicts and aſſaults,</hi> ſome are leſſe ſeene, ſome are more openly hoſtile. <hi>The leſſe manifeſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayling of vs is,</hi> when hee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth his perſon, or his ſtrength: For Satan often commeth in the perſon of a friend, ſometimes in an Angels of light, ſometimes in the perſons of Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted; and hee is like that policy of the <hi>Gibeonites, Ioſ.</hi> 9 9. Like the King of Iſrael who fought with <hi>Aram</hi> in other apparell:<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.30.</note> or like as if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17283:23"/> a Man of warre meeting an enemy ſhould hang out the ſame colours with them, and ſet men ſpeaking the ſelfe ſame language, and of the ſelfe ſame habite with their enemies, and ſo ſhould board them and ſinke them at vnawares; theſe therfore muſt a little bee opened. <hi>Firſt, hee commeth and cloſeth as a friend,</hi> inſinuating, as if hee bare vs more good will then God. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3. God knoweth if your eies ſhould be opened, &amp;c. ſo to Chriſt, Maſter ſpare thy ſelfe: but mark what Chriſt replyeth, Goe behinde me Satan. So hee commeth to another<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What? he hath abuſed thee; doe not let him doe thee that wrong, others will bee
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17283:23"/> heartened to doe thee the like. So when he perſwades couetouſnes, You muſt haue ſome thing more then this: You haue, and may haue a great charge: ſo to him that would double his diligence, What neede you ſo diſeaſe your ſelfe? God forbid none but ſuch great paines takers ſhould com to heauen. Thus hee would with a friendly parlie, with a <hi>Ioabs</hi> kiſſe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly betray vs. Secondly, he hath ſometimes <hi>taken on him the perſon of an Angel of light,</hi> in wordes which hee can ſpeake good. <hi>Marke</hi> 1.24. and 5.7, Thou art the Son of God. The maid with the ſpirit of diuination ſaith, You are the ſeruants of the moſt high God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.16.</note> but he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17283:24"/> the words, and vſeth them vnto euill ends, to win himſelfe credit in his lying, or weaken the truth of them by his confeſſing: ſo in <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine domini</hi> beginneth much wickedneſſe. Secondly, hee will ſet vs vnſeaſonably and buſie vs about good works, and thus hee did <hi>Martha, Luke</hi> 10.40. making her ſo buſie in the entertainement, that ſhee had no leaſure for the better worke, that which <hi>Mary</hi> choſe. This is his wickedneſſe, and he alwaies doth it either to iuſtle out a better work, or to draw-in with that good ſom greater euill. So in the Church, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reade often and are thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of good things, but the Diuell doth draw them to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17283:24"/> this, that they might not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the worke in hand. Thirdly, hee will perſwade to euill vnder the ſhew of good: thus hee will make vs vnder the pretence of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and moderation, be like thoſe who were neither hotte nor colde, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to be ſpued out of Gods mouth: He will with a ſhew of zeale fetch vs off to murther. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.54. Hee did the diſciples, and thus hee beguileth ſuch who will reform without authority, and the Browniſts who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled with a falſe ſpirit of zeale, make ſeparation: ſo by perſwading prouidence, hee doth fill the heart with couetouſneſſe: ſo by perſwading perfection, hee
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17283:25"/> foileth in will-worſhip: ſo theſe doctrins of Diuels for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding meates, mariage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly, are broached vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of chaſtity, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence; invocation of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and doubting, vnder pretence of humility. <hi>Col.</hi> 2. and vnwritten truths with curious queſtions, vnder pretence of profound lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: ſuch like doctrine. <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.24 ſo ſtiled, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therefore the depth of Satan. 4. By diſſwading that which is truely good, as if it were a vice: thus repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and leading new liues, and taking vp the orders of God, this is new-fanglenes, and leuity: thus doing any dutie that is not ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued, it is diſſwaded as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17283:25"/> ſingularity and pride; thus zeale is madneſſe, as in Chriſts practice cenſured. <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.21. And <hi>Paul</hi> vvas thought to be mad through much learning: thus the lawfull remedy is calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as vncleanneſſe; depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on Gods providence is counted tempting him: as in that example of <hi>Ahaz, Eſay</hi> 7.12. Particular faith is pride, &amp;c. And thus he doth ſette fine colours on foule cloathes, and like an Angel of light doth beguile vs. 3. Hee taketh on him the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Saints departed: as apparitions for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of erronious doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, do fully aſſure vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond leſſe apparant action is, his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſembling of his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17283:26"/> ſtrength;</hi> ſomtime eleuating, leſſening his power: as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our Lord hath foyled him in vs, hee will make vs if he vvere eaſily withſtood that vvee might after a ſort com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him, that then wee might wex ſecure, and bee betrayed, 2. By diſſembled flight, like the ſtratagem v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Iud.</hi> 20. Hee will ſeeme as fled, but then hee playeth the <hi>Parthian,</hi> hee fighteth moſt dangerouſly: Thus many that haue beene prodigall, giuen to women, are grown better husbands, and become new men; the Diuell ſeemeth to bee fled: but if they be not new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures indeede, having new hearts, hungring after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17283:26"/> of God, in Chriſt, the Diuell hath them farre ſurer then before.</p>
            <p>So in <hi>Saul,</hi> when the evil ſpirit came vpon him; when <hi>Dauid</hi> played, the Diuell ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be gone, but alas no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe. So ſome haue bin troubled in conſcience, and they haue skinned all ouer in their manner, all is quiet now: but let them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, for if they haue not met with the right cure, the Diuell by lying ſtill, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling flight, will make them ſecure to their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>Now, vvee cannot finde them out better, then by conſidering of warlike ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, to one whereof the holy Ghoſt here hath refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17283:27"/> Novv theſe are diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three bands: for they are either in prying out, or in concealement, or in matter of attempt. For the firſt, the diuell doth pry into vs, and knovveth vs but too vvell, hee is named from knovvledge, yea he hath his intelligences fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> every look, geſture, affection,  that vve may ſay as <hi>Aram</hi> did, We can doo nothing in our bed-chamber, but he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth it, 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 2.11.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, for conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he is as ſubtill to finde vs out as to hide himſelfe; and therefore carrieth his matters ſo, that the moſt are murderd by him before they vviſt who hurt them; being like the Fox, vvho entereth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17283:27"/> fetching leaps into her hole, that one may not bee able to trace her to her den ſhe lieth in: which will appear more in his more apparent practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. His more apparent pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices are theſe; Firſt, his ambuſhment: and this word doth note a ſtratagem vſed by the Iſraelites againſt <hi>Ai:</hi> this is the noted courſe of the divell, that hee ſhall bite at the heele, and come vpon vs behinde our backe as it were. Thus ſomtime he tempteth vs to groſſe neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of our duty or the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but he commeth vpon vs ſtealing, with indevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or eying man in the performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of duty, ſeeking to corrupt the manner or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: but theſe things not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17283:28"/> taking place, hee hath lying in ambuſh, pride and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; with which, after perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming any good duty, we are ready to be overtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>A ſecond ſtratagem, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine courſe of victuall from the beſieged, or to take away weapons from the enemy;</hi> the one practiced againſt <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> the other by the Pſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims againſt Iſrael, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.19. Now this is the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Satan againſt vs, to famiſh vs if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for now at a ſermon, the milk, bread, and meat of our ſoules, is dealt forth by Gods Steward; but hovv many doth the divell keep from taſting one mouth ful? ſom vaniſh in wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring thoughts: ſome ſit like pillars: ſome if
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17283:28"/> they bee held too long, or haue it not trimly diſhed forth, fall out vvith their meat, and vvill none: ſo many vvorthy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants hee maketh afraid to touch the ſacrament; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable performance, indiſpoſitions ſo trouble them. So he doth labour no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, then to vvring our vveapons out of our hands; as praier, vvhat a deal of diſcomfort doe vvee knovve in it? ſuch ſvvarms of thoughts impertinent, ſuch miſts, ſuch loſſe of all comfortable ſenſe? But the divell knovveth, that a prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er preferred in the obedience of faith, though out of the deeps of death and ſpirituall thraldome, is tvvice accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17283:29"/> but his drift is to make vs lay aſide praier. So faith: vvhat is the matter that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevving our faith vvee haue ſome trial preſently that ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs more then euer? The matter the divell aimeth at is, to make vs by ſuch conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall foiles, after renuing our faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bee vveary of this, and ſo caſt our ſhield from vs.</p>
            <p>A third ſtratagem in ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies is, to get the contrary forces out of their hould, or to diſorder their march and battell array, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Iud.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>Novv this is the diuels politicke practice: for our wal &amp; mount is firſt our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in the word of promiſe, and threatning of God if vve ſin; 2. Our conſtant courſe in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17283:29"/> good exerciſes. Novv the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel vvil dravv vs from theſe, as thoſe in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. vvho vvere brought to ſay, It is in vain to ſerue the Lord: as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah,</hi> the divell brought her to make a peraduenture of death that vvas ſo peremto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily threatned, &amp; then ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed her deadly. So <hi>Dauid</hi> vvas vvont to pray thrice a day, and take times for ſuch devotions: but the diuel (as it is probable in 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2.) had cauſed him to com from his trench, and then did preſently vvound him.</p>
            <p>The fourth ſtratagem is, Spreading of falſe terrors. <hi>Iud.</hi> 7. <hi>Gedcon</hi> vvith a fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhovve did ſo aſtoniſh the enemy, that they turned one againſt the other: thus
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17283:30"/> the diuell doth often mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal many cauſeleſſe terrors, as he makes others preſume vvhen they ſhould tremble. Hence it commeth, that hee maketh Gods dear chriſtian children be ſometime trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with fear vvhether they are in the fauour of GOD, vvhether they euer had true grace vvhether they haue not ſinned againſt the holy Ghoſt. So in particular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons if one will make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of vnlawfull gain, he will feare them with pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, They ſhall not be able to liue: ſo, if they bee liberall, he wil caſt in this fear, They may want themſelues: ſo, if they defend an innocent helpleſſe perſon, he will bid them looke what they doo,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17283:30"/> they may draw an old houſe on their heads: and he doth fill the eyes of the ſpirit with ſuch diſguiſed bug-beares.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift ſtratagem is, to ſend-in ſom ſmall forces, or ſuborn ſom treacherous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments which may betray all: thus the divell will often faſten ſmall ſinnes on vs, to bring vs on to greater; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orne falſe brethren.</p>
            <p>Now what is the vſe of all this, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> but to ſtirre vs vp to looke about vs? ſeeing wee haue ſo ſecret and ſo ſubtill an adverſary inſtructed with a thouſand arts to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent vs, what need haue we to be innocent as Doues, but wiſe as Serpents? Now, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> if you will ask, Hovv <hi>wee may bee k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt ſafe.?</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Learn to feare
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17283:31"/> and ſuſpect the euill one: this is the Sentinell of the ſoule, vvhich maketh diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the aduerſary. Bee watchfull, &amp;c. Credulity is full of perill, but vviſe ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ſecureth from danger. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let vs keep vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our houlds; keepe the threatning vvord vvithin thy hart, &amp; the daily courſe of chriſtian duty, and they ſhall not bee able to hurt: but aboue all things, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> hould Chriſt and his vviſdome by faith: for (<hi>Pro.</hi> 8.12.) hee dvvelleth with prudence, he findeth out counſels, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of vviſdome is in him. If vve had to deale vvith ſome crafty B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oaker, vvee vvould ioine the vviſeſt head vvee could meet vvith againſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17283:31"/> him: but get Chriſt the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the father, and no vviſedome ſhall bee able to hurt thee.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, pray with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. Achitophels</hi> ſtratagems, in the time of peace, vvere like the Oracles of God; but what ſaid <hi>Dauid,</hi> Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the wiſedome of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitophel.</hi> 2. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> This ſhould teach vs tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes to God, who in his word doth make diſcouerie of ſuch like ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems. If one diſcouer to vs any vvily device of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, we are glad, nothing doth come to vs more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: ſo nothing ſhould more reioyce vs, who are in our vvarfnre, then to know what plots our enemies haue contriued againſt vs.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17283:32"/> 
               <hi>Forewarned, forearmed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The reaſon followeth. For we wreſtle not against fleſh and blood, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In which, three things are to be conſidered.</hi> 1. Who are the vvreſtlers. 2. The wreſtling it ſelfe. 3. The Antagoniſts that vvreſtle with vs. But the vvordes are difficult: therefore it may bee asked, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> What it this wreſtling? <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. A ſpeech borrowed from an earthly exerciſe, to ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe a ſpirituall courſe. For vvreſtling againſt one, is the putting of a bodily force forth, that I may caſt down from his ſtanding, and lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long him againſt whom I vvreſtle: ſo the life of a Chriſtian, is the receiuing of a ſpirituall impreſſion
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17283:32"/> from the powers of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vvhich they make to this end, that they may caſt vs downe from the ſtate of faith, righteouſneſſe, &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedneſſe; to an vnbeleeuing, vnrighteous, &amp; curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it may be asked, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> how it is ſaid vvee fight not againſt fleſh and blood, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle ſaith, Hee fought vvith beaſts at <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> &amp;c. that is, ſauage men, of beaſtly quality; ſeeing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that men make vs no ſmall exerciſe? <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The meaning is not ſimply to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them; but after a ſort: in this manner, vvee haue not onely, or principally fleſh and blood. The like ſpeech is to bee found elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17283:33"/> God ſaith by <hi>Samuel,</hi> they haue not caſt thee off, but me: that is, not thee on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or principally. 1. <hi>Samuel,</hi> 8.7.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, it may be asked, how the Apoſtle can ſay, that theſe do thus moleſt vs, the powers of darkneſſe; when <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.13. wee are ſaid to bee deliuered from them. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.11. The Prince of this world is ſayd to bee caſt forth, and iudged?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> We are deliuered from the raging power of them, not power of tempting for exerciſe ſake. 2. Wee haue deliuerance, and Satan is ſubdued in part: for the Scripture ſpeaketh of things begun, and in dooing; as
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17283:33"/> done: in ſome meaſure wee haue deliuerance, but not perfect. Wee ſee not all things ſubiect to Chriſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.8. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. Satan is not, but ſhortly ſhall be troden down vnder our feet; This ſerues in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. But the laſt part of the verſe is difficult, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore requireth more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar examination. For the ſumme therefore of it, here is a <hi>deſcription of the Diuell &amp; his Angels,</hi> which are the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylants of vs in the way of ſaluation. <hi>Now they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed three waies.</hi> 1. From the reſpect of power they haue in regard of this world, and that particularly called principalities, and powers; generally, call'd worldly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17283:34"/> which is expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by way of correction, gouernours of the darkneſſe of this world. 2. They are deſcribed from their nature. 1. Their eſſence, ſpirits. 2. Their quality, wicked. 3. From the place of them, in high places, or heauenly places;</p>
            <p>The aire called by the name of heauen, as the fowles of the ayre are called the fowles of heauen. Now for the meaning, wee muſt open the words. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 1. What is the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt theſe three words. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> They do lay downe a difference of degrees in evill Angels, which is plainely taught in Scripture. 2. The exact dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, is not comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17283:34"/> by vs, though the Lord hath reuealed it. We ſay it is taught in the Scriptures, that if any thing bee found out pertinent and ſound, it may be knowne to haue been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by God. 2. We ſay, that theſe things, though in Scripture not fully concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, we may teach modeſty, and conſcience of our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, when we come to the Scripture; that ſo wee may ſeeke to haue our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnlocked. 2. That we may baniſh the pride of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wiſe aboue that which is written, when we cannot conceiue all things vvritten. 3. That we may teach, that the perſpicuous knowledge of this doctrine of Angels, is kept till we ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:17283:35"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But yet with reuerence ſo farre as the word of God doth holde forth light, wee may impart that wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</p>
            <p>Firſt, therefore you muſt knowe that <hi>there are two ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall kingdomes in the world.</hi> The one of light, God, Chriſt. The other of Satan, called alſo the power of darkneſſe. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. Who hath deliuered vs from the power of darkneſſe. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. Now as the kingdome of God is not in word, but in power, in righteouſneſſe, peace, and ioy: <hi>So the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom of Satan is in power; which eſpecially ſtands in foure things.</hi> In ſinne, which as a ſpiritual iudgement he doth execute: In the curſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14 That
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17283:35"/> hee might deſtroy through death, him that had the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of death: in inflicting euils apparantly, euill in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſoule, goods: and in giuing things good in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; yet beſtowed in Gods fierce wrath. And thus hee beſtoweth through Gods iuſt iudgement, the glory and riches of this world. For when God wil let a man thriue in ſinne, the Diuell vvill ſerue him in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſe, aboue that his heart can deſire. This is his proper power in regarde of the wicked. Now in reſpect of the godly, he hath a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to exerciſe them with ſundry tentations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, you muſt ſette downe, that in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17283:36"/> of euill Angels, there are ſome in order before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; that is granted of all. More particularly, there is one vniuerſall commander of the reſt, and Prince as it were of the whole world: therefore the Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſingularly of him, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him the Diuell, with an eminency aboue his Angels: Satan, the Prince of this world, as our Sauiour doth often call him, in <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. There are Princes, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſpirits in Nations and Countries vnder him. Thus the Scripture teacheth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10.13. The Prince of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> where he ſpeaketh of an Angel hauing power in that countrey; hauing power to worke ſo in the ſonnes of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17283:36"/> diſobedience, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Church was hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. And theſe are princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally vnder the Prince of the whole world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it may bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably conceiued, that in Countries there are of infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour authority vnder them, and they are powers. For in earthly kingdomes (when theſe two words are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) the one doth ſignifie principall gouernours, the other ſecond ones, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delegate vnder them: So that, <hi>the firſt word may note the Prince of the whole world, and ſuch as are principall ouer nations vnder him. The ſecond, ſuch as are in authority vnder them, to execute Gods ſpiritual iudgement of ſinne and curſe,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17283:37"/> and haue power of tempting the Saints. Now the third word doth comprehend both the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as the generall doth the kindes vnder it: For both the Princes of this world, Princes nationall, and powers inferior to them, all are worldly gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now hee openeth the foundation of this their power; leſt they ſhould bee thought gouernours, ſuch as are the ſons of the moſt high, and haue receiued magiſtracie for the good of men; hee ſaith, they be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the world, by reaſon of the darkneſſe in it: or by the world, I mean the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinne, all kinde of curſes, and ſpirituall tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The ſecond thing
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17283:37"/> they are deſcribed from, is their nature. Firſt, they are ſpirituall: that is, intelligences that cannot be ſeene with eye; ſubtle and powerfull. 2. For their qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, wicked; ſuch as haue at leaſt eminently in them al wickednes. The third thing is the place; the doctrine of which, you may remember in theſe three concluſions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are caſt out of heauen; which was their firſt habitation, <hi>Iude</hi> 6. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the place appointed to them all (and where ſom are reſerued to the laſt day) is hell, or the deep. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. For if God ſpared not the Angels, &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.31. And they beſought him that hee would not commaund
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17283:38"/> them to goe out into the deepe, that is into hell. For theſe guilty perſons are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned before execution.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that Gods iuſt diſpoſition is ſuch, that for executing his ſpiritual iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; curſes on the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; trying with tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions his owne children, ſome of them are in the earth. <hi>Apoca.</hi> 12.12. For the Diuell is come downe in great rage. <hi>Iob</hi> 1. The Diuel compaſſeth the earth. Some are in the ayre, as in this place to hinder the ſauing hearing of Gods word; and in the ſtory of <hi>Iob,</hi> they ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp tempeſts,</p>
            <p>Now then the ſumme of theſe wordes, may more largely in this maner be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17283:38"/> You haue good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to put on the armour of God: for all of vs who haue receiued to beleeue, &amp; haue through faith our hearts purified to obedience; what is our life, but a continuall conflict (wreſtle) and who are thoſe that encounter vs? Not fleſh &amp; blood, for then wee needed not armour of ſuch high proofe, forged by God himſelfe. But thoſe that ſtriue with vs, are ſuch, as if you looke at their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, they haue a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome amongſt men, the Prince of the whole world; vnder him national Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; theſe haue principali<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and ſecondarie powers vnder them. Theſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers, theſe all
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17283:39"/> of them are great gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the world, doe all of them reſiſt vs, yet I wold not haue you take them ſuch as haue a magiſtracy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the outward man, for the good of them, as world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes; vvho are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called gods. But the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency they haue amongſt men, is by reaſon of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Gods ſpirituall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, curſes which God vvill haue executed, and temptations wherwith God will haue his children exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; gouernours of the darkenes of this world. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, for their nature, they are not weake fleſh, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and therefore ſubtle, &amp; mighty to ſpread their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, wherewith they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17283:39"/> are repleniſhed.</p>
            <p>Finally, they are ſuch to whom (caſt out of heauen) though the deepe hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth; yet the Lord by his iuſt diſpenſation (that his iudgements may bee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the wicked, and his children tryed) doth let them bee in the earth, and houer ouer our heads in the ayre, in great abundance, prying into vs, and ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the vantage of the place againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then wee ſee heere, that no man, whatſoeuer his worthineſſe is, or graces, but is encountred by Satan. Our parents were ſet-on in ſtate of innocency: Chriſt; <hi>He deſired to winnow the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: for of all other he is the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17283:40"/> moſt oppoſite to ſuch,</hi> as vvho vvill ſtill be buſieſt vvhere he hath leaſt to doo. And no marvell: for, the Saints haue received Gods preſſe-mony, and bound themſelves by ſacrament to fight againſt him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, the Saints are paſſed (by the povver of God) out of his kingdome, and therefore hee doth ſpite them, as not of his family: as dogs vſe to bark, and bite not thoſe of the houſe they are in, but ſtrangers: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the Saints finally haue the goul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den graces of God, vvhich are the treaſure hee vvould robbe from them. Theeues break not into poore cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but houſes vvhich are fulleſt of treaſure: ſo Satan vvil offer to break into thoſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17283:40"/> hearts vvhich God hath ſilld vvith his ſpirituall treaſure; there is booty for his malice to prey vpon.</p>
            <p>This therefore muſt bee laid down, that <hi>All the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full finde ſpirituall enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt them:</hi> for though ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time hee goe away for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.13; though there be olde men aſwell as yong: yet this hindreth not, but that it may bee affirmed of all, that they haue their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſtill begirting them, and aſſailing them, vvhen they hope for advantage by it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Which doth refute the vaine iudgement of the world, which ſavoureth not the things of God: for wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this is the eſtate of all Saints, they count them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17283:41"/> fooliſh, or humorous, troubled with they knowe not what, or think that they are ſome notorious ſinners, if they bee in their mindes moleſted. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it muſt teach all of vs who are weak in grace, of ſmall growth, not to wonder if we be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: for if the green wood eſcape not, what ſhall vvee, dry in compariſon, bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we muſt bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed (though of never ſuch proceeding) not to lay aſide our armour, ſeeing that wee are ſtill ſubiect to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaulted: <hi>Nunquam bella bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, nunquam, certamina de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, wee muſt ſee what is the courſe of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17283:41"/> life: it is a conflicting courſe, or wraſtling conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; power of darkneſſe ſeeking to throwe him from faith, holineſſe, bleſſednes, to ſinne and a curſed eſtate: our life is a warfare. The life of all men generally is full of commotion, <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.1; much more of them, who for op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in this world, are of all men the moſt miſerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, his life &amp; courſe was a warfare; I haue fought a good fight, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 7. <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 32.28, beeing a patterne of all true-hearted Iſraelites, whoſe lives are a wraſtling by teares and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, againſt all ſpirituall wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. Sometimes it is not manifeſt to the eye of the world, that the matter is ſo
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17283:42"/> with them as it is, they are thought to haue faire lives; but many a man, merry in company, hath a ſhrewe at home: ſo the Saints, though they may ſeeme to bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, haue that in ſecret which doth fill their hearts with ſighes, and their eyes with teares, ſomething out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or inward, or both, wherwith they alwaies wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. <hi>It must bee thus:</hi> for the fire of grace is like the heat of the body in this, if the heat of the ſtomach had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to wraſtle with, it would bring all the body, &amp; ſo it ſelfe, into an vtter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: if Gods grace had not ſomething without or within, exerciſing of it, with which it might wraſtle, it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17283:42"/> could not, in this eſtate vve are in, be preſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, theſe wraſtlings in temptation doo bring vs to knowe the povver, vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and faithfulneſſe of God, to knovve our ſelues and others.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, vvithout ſtriving, vvee muſt not be crovvned, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. and if any man ſtriue for a maſtery, &amp;c: for though this is not the cauſe, tis the vvay to our glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> The vvhich doth, firſt, let ſuch knovve vvho lead plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant lives, and are at eaſe in Sion, vvho are not poured from veſſell to veſſell, but vvalke on, as if their league and covenant were ſtricken vvith hell, that their courſe is not the life of Chriſtians
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17283:43"/> (this is a vvraſtling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting eſtate) and it is a ſigne that the ſtrong man poſſeſſeth the houſe, that all is ſo quiet.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, this muſt make vs, though vvee finde much ſtrife in the vvay, that vvee muſt not faint, nay vve muſt take heart: for this, that vve finde ſuch a conflict, is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that vvee are the Lords, and that he hath caſt out the ſtrong one of the vvorld. But you vvill ſay: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> May eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that findeth a ſtrife be ſure of this? Naturall men haue a fight often in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, condemning that they doo, approuing the contrary; <hi>Video meliora, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boque. Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> There is a fight betvveene the naturall light
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17283:43"/> of conſcience, and the ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all courſes. But <hi>by theſe three rules we may diſcerne the fight of the ſpirit and fleſh from it:</hi> Firſt, our ſtrife is cauſed not from enormous ſwarving, but from the corrupt quality which infecteth vs through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, our birth, ſin, the lavv of evill vvhich dvvelleth in the members. Novv this is a thing vvhich the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not deſcry.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the light of na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture cauſeth a ſtrife, vvhen vve doo ſome groſſe things, or in groſſe neglect: but the ſtrife of the ſpirit is in good things, againſt the not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect performance of them: thus <hi>Pauls</hi> fight vvas, that he could not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the things hee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17283:44"/> vvould, in the manner hee deſired. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Third<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, this natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall accuſing vvas in vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies: but this ſtrife of the ſpirit vvee finde by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, vve never knew vvhat it meant, till, giving our names to Chriſt, vve did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour in all things to ſerue him. Hence it is, that they vvho novv moſt complaine, vvill ſay, they once thought themſelues vvell enough, &amp; euery little thing too much forvvardnes, before GOD touched them more neerly.</p>
            <p>Novv follovveth the third thing, vvho it is that doth in all things ſtriue againſt vs? The Diuell and his Angels. This the Scripture hath of olde taught, God putting enmity between the ſerpent
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17283:44"/> and the ſeed of the woman, and therefore the Diuell by eminency is cald the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.5. And his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred is ſo great, that there is nothing from which he will not take occaſion to be dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with vs. For as God doth worke the perfecting of his by the buffeting of the Diuell: ſo Satan doth turne the beſt graces of God to matter of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation. But for the clearing of this, wee muſt knowe that the Diuell doth ſometimes tempt vs immediately: as <hi>Ananias, Acts</hi> 5.3. <hi>Iudas, Luke</hi> 22.2. Secondly, thus: in tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of blaſphemy, ſelfe murther, in the iudgement which hee bringeth, and in this maner Chriſt was temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17283:45"/> in two temptations; &amp; <hi>Iobs</hi> body and goods were touched by him.</p>
            <p>Now bee is plainely wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtling in this kinde, but in thoſe things wherein hee is not the next moouer, yet is the firſt and more remote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent; and therefore they may be ſaide in ſome things to wreſtle againſt vs: As when the things of this world arme themſelues, or the perſons in the world doe make vs matter; Satan is a principall worker in them all. The laſt branch is to bee ſhewed in the next doctrine: the things of the world, as glory, riches, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, muſt not be conſidered as naked things, but as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments by his vſe lifted
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17283:45"/> vp, the force they haue of bewitching and inueigling our hearts from God. Thus hee vſed the glory of the world to Chriſt as a bait to take him with. Thus, 1. <hi>Timothie</hi> 6.9. riches are his ſnare; thus the apple deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the eie and taſte, was an argument hee preferred to our firſt parents: and that life in theſe things, which ſo worketh on the naturall man, commeth partly from Satan, which is alſo crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame croſſe of Chriſt, by which he was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued. 2. Saint <hi>Iames</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam</hi> 1.14.</note> ſaith, that our concupiſcence withdrawing vs, wee are tempted of it: but though it be ſo fruitfull a parent that it can without mid-wifery
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17283:46"/> bring forth alone: yet wee muſt conceiue it ſo, that for the moſt part, our luſt is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and excited by theſe euil ſpirits, they blowe the coals vp, and are the fires of the ſinne whereof our concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence is the mother: be not angry, giue not place to the Diuell, the Diuell therefore ſtirreth vp anger, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.26.27. <hi>Dauids</hi> heart did ſwell, but the Diuell perſwaded &amp; mooued it, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. The widowes following luſt, goe after the Diuell, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.15. And as it is alwaies true that when wee doe any good thing, wee doe it from the principles of grace in vs, yet the ſpirit giueth vs the will and the deede: ſo when wee doe euill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17283:46"/> by our concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, the Diuell for the moſt part doth kindle, and excite the ſin which dwels in vs, that we may ſay it is true, The Diuel is, by himſelfe, and by the things of this world, &amp; by concupiſcence, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall tempter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Now more particularly, that he ſaith we wreſtle not againſt fleſh and blood, it doth teach vs, <hi>that in thoſe things men doe or ſpeake offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely to vs, our principall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie is not man. Paul</hi> had much oppoſition by men, yet hee ſaith we wreſtle not againſt men: he ſaw worſe enemies in them then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: men did perſecute the Saints, but <hi>Reuel.</hi> 2.10. the holy Ghoſt ſaith, the Diuell
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17283:47"/> doth caſt them into priſon: the falſe teachers did ſeduce the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11. the holy Ghoſt ſaith, Satan did beguile them: the Damoſell and men that cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Peter</hi> to the denyall of his Maſter, were not his chiefe enemies, but the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that deſired to winnow him, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.21. So the <hi>Caldeans</hi> and <hi>Sabeans,</hi> that ſpoyled <hi>Iobs</hi> goods, were not the chiefe againſt him, but Satan by them. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell doth like fowlers who go with their ſtalking horſe twixt them and the fowle, that they may ſhoote more ſecurely: ſo hee doth put men, ſometime our friends, ſomtime good men, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are nothing afraid, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17283:47"/> vs and him, that hee may work his miſchiefe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Wherfore ſeeing it is thus, when any perſon doth offend vs, or prouoke our ſpirit, let vs not ſo much looke at them, as at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie the Diuell doth ſhew in them, who doth labour to winow vs, weaken our faith, break our patience by thoſe things; and this wold make vs not take to heart, ſo much perſons that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs, but bend our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces moſt againſt thoſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal enemies, whoſe trunks &amp; inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts the other are. <hi>Saul</hi> left hunting <hi>Dauid</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heard the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were vpon him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 2. Seeing the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel doth euen make men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his wickednes,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17283:48"/> let vs by the way take good heed, that hee doe not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuent vs: the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee will winde in him ſelfe, when wee haue no ill purpoſe in it; as <hi>Peter</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt to ſpare himſelfe. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> being ſeuere to the inceſtuous perſon, the Diuell would haue vſed this their courſe to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming of him with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the Diuell, with his Angels are called powers and principalities. Wee ſee the euill Angels haue a great ſtroke in the frame of this preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill world, in ordering (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſordering) of ſtates and kingdomes: theſe are not emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie titles,, but giuen them from a powerfull action they haue in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17283:48"/> the hearts of men, by Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion:</hi> And the ſame muſt be gathered when hee is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Prince of this world, yea, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. the god of this world; his vſurpation, and the ſpirits of euill men yeelding him no leſſe. Great is their power in keeping out good, keeping in euill, procuring iudgement: and hee doth ſcoure thorough Court and Countrey, for this purpoſe. Thus he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked <hi>Dauid</hi> by ſinne to lay the people naked to Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.1. And Satan ſtood vp againſt Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell. Thus hee laboured to cutte off the hopes of the Church, by ſtirring vp euill Princes, to entrap <hi>Daniel</hi> in the matter of his religion.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17283:49"/> 
               <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.5. Thus hee ſtood at the right hand of <hi>Iehoſuah</hi> to reſiſt him. <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.2. Prince, Prieſt, and People, hee worketh in them all to holde vp his owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſtabliſheth all things that ſerue for it; as on the contrary to keepe out light &amp; truth, and all means which ſhold befriend theſe. Hence it was, that the beſt Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> neuer made a thorough reformation: hence, that in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries receiuing the Goſpell, as in <hi>Germany,</hi> there haue beene ſuch bones of diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as ſubſcription to their bookes of concord, the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of diſcord. For <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.24.25. the Diuell ſoweth tares, when good ſeede is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17283:49"/> ſowen by the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Wherefore ſeeing that theſe ſpirits haue ſuch a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in this world, we muſt not wonder at ſuch ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Which of the great ones beleeue on him? <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.48. You ſee your calling, not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.26. For then the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell could not haue ſo great a ſway in the kingdome of this world, if he ſhould not holde great perſonages (for the moſt part) ſure to him. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Againe, it letteth vs ſee, that the ſuccesfull proceeding of the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, will not come off eaſily; for theſe powers doe oppoſe againſt it. And ſuch
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17283:50"/> as are light of beleefe in this point, it proceedeth from ignorance: They doe not knowe the power, and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Diuels kingdom. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> But the third and principall vſe is, to ſtirre vs vp to pray that God would make theſe powers fall down like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from heauen: that God would binde vp theſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of darkneſſe, and ſend forth his good Angels to watch for the good of Church and Countrey. If the Diuell be ſo buſie to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the perſonall progreſſe of a private man, what will he do to withſtand the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py eſtate of a whole nation, if God ſhould not rebuke him?</p>
            <p>The third thing to bee
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17283:50"/> marked hence, is, that hee ſaith they be gouernours of the darkneſſe of this world: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Obſerue hence, <hi>that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doe liue in the ſtate of darkneſſe, they are vnder the Diuels power. Theſe are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the one as the foundation of the other: and before wee haue deliuerance from the one, we cannot be freed from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Act.</hi> 26.18, To open their eyes, that they may turn from darknes to light, and from the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to God, &amp;c. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture affirmeth of one, who heareth the word, and commeth not to the affectiue knowledge of it (ſo to learne Chriſt, as the truth is in Chriſt) that hee is in the hands of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17283:51"/> God of this world. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. In whom the God of this world hath blinded their mindes, that is, of the Infidels: that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt, which is the image of God, ſhould not ſhine vnto them; for ignorance is the very foundation of the Diuels kingdome. Againe, whoſo liueth in the darkneſſe of ſinne, is of the Diuell. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8, He that commiteth ſinne is of the Diuell: and whoſo is ſubiect to Gods curſe (as euery one not truely belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing is) is as yet vnder the power of Satan: for hee is Gods executioner; euen as we may ſay, if a man bee led pinioned vp the ladder, and haue a handkerchiefe knit
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:17283:51"/> before his eyes, that hee is in the hands of the hangman. If one be in the dungeon at the Caſtle, with boults on him, we may ſay he is vnder the power of the Iayler: ſo if this vaile be knit before the eyes of the mind and ſo the face couered: If one do liue in vnrighteouſnes &amp; vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, bound with the bands of many treſpaſſes (whoſe ſins you ſhall looſe) If one lie in the little eaſe of an euill conſcience, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be in a drunken ſleep and feele nothing, or if hee be waking: ſuch a party is in the power of Satan; for the Diuell is but the Iayler and hangman to the Iuſtice of God.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Wherfore let vs examine
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17283:52"/> our ſelues, and conſider how it is with vs: for wee would bleſſe our ſelues, wee would be loth to haue one neer vs, come into ſuch condition for the outward man, ſo ſhamefull, ſo miſerable: but let vs look our ſoules be not in worſe hands. It is ſo with vs, that the eye ſees not, the heart dreads not, yea vvee count our chaines and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment the onely liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and to knowe nothing, nor to care for any thing in matters of religion, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant life. Men loue darknes better then light; &amp; becauſe they haue euer beene in this hell, they thinke there is no other heauen: but if you be thus impriſoned in darknes of vnderſtanding, in vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:17283:52"/> vnder Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure; knowe this, there will come a day of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too ſoon vpon you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, wee muſt ſtirre vp our ſelues to thankfulnes, who are now made light in the Lord: for if the divell's territories reach no further then darknes, we are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his kingdom, who haue received the light of vnderſtanding and holineſs in any meaſure. This made the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12, break out into thankſgiving. Is it not a merry time when the gaole-delivery comes, when their fees are payed, when their Irons are took off, and themſelues diſcharged, that they now may walk at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? it is merry with them,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17283:53"/> though they hault a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: ſo with vs, though wee limp by reaſon of the chains wee carried ſo long, vvee ſhould tell this treaſure of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The fourth thing to bee marked from hence is, that the divels are called ſpiritual wickednes, or ſpirits of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, that <hi>As wee will haue nothing to doe with the diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, ſo must we flee from his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: if we l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t-in his wickedneſſe, we cannot but giue him enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment:</hi> for, the diuell co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto vs in ſuggeſtions of vnrighteouſnes; if vvee conſent to them, vvee enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the divell. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> when they conſented to the wicked motions the divell inſpired into them;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17283:53"/> the divell is ſaid to fill the heart of the one, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the other, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.3. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.3. and not onely of theſe enormous ſinners, but of all that walke in euill: and for the diuell he hath a dwelling in them; The ſtrong man armed keepeth the houſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. yea, the godly if they liſten to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, they giue place to the diuell, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4: for looke, as when God knocketh at our harts by a holy motion, if wee open in obeying, the Lord doth come, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dwell in vs, <hi>Apo.</hi> 3.21. So when theſe wicked ſpirits doo reach out their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vnto vs, if vvee conſent to it, they come to poſſeſſe vs after a ſort, and haue a
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:17283:54"/> dvvelling in vs. But, you will ſay then, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Who hath not the divell dvvelling vvith him? for, vvho doth not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten yeeld to evil? <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> None but doo ſomtime giue place to him, yet he dvvelleth not alike in all. Thoſe that with full conſent of heart receiue his ſuggeſtions, he hath full hould in them: but the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvhen they giue place to him, they let him come into the ſuburbs and out-parts: but becauſe Chriſt dwelleth in their hearts by faith; the tovver being kept, hee is, by the renevving of their faith and repentance, forced to retire. This therefore is to bee marked, that ſeeing the diuell is nothing but a ſpirit of vvickednes, that by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17283:54"/> conſenting to vvickednes, vvee let-in the divell vnto vs. Novv then take heed: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> men vvill ſpet at his name, and bleſſe themſelves from having to doe vvith him: but if you giue place to vvrath, ſtomachfulnes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, pride, good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the ſuggeſtions of this kinde, you receiue him into your boſome, and are notably fooliſh; like as men ſhould be afraid at the name of fire, but care not to bee burned vvith the heat of it. You muſt not conceiue of the diuell as of ſom hideous ſhape, as if hee ſhould come like as you dreſſe him in May-games and Pageants, vvith hornes, in an ox-hide, and cloven feet, ſquirting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17283:55"/> fire; no ſaith hee, I vvill goe to ſuch a one, I vvill bee a ſpirit of vntruth, I vvill be a ſpirit of error, 1. <hi>Reg. vlt.</hi> 22. a ſpirit of couetouſnes, of pride, of malice; I vvill ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt theſe things: Conſent to theſe vvickedneſſes, and you receiue the ſpirit which prompteth you vvith them, to your vnderſtanding. And the Lord teach vs to hate vvickednes, even as the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell that is a ſpirit of it, full of it, and labouring to fill vs vvith it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, that they are in high places, are aboue vs, Hence learne circumſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for, ſeeing vve ly naked to the vievv of them, vvee muſt bee carefull, that they ſpy nothing in vs to their
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17283:55"/> advantage: againe, vvhat are they? not only lion-like enemies, but malitious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters.</p>
            <p>Novv if a Promoter, that ſhould bear vs no good vvil, ſhould ſtand ouer our heads, vvould vve not be watchful; knovving, that every fault vvould be informed againſt vs? ſo the divell is no other then a malitious accuſer of vs; and theſe ſpirituall vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes hang hovering o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our heads: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vvherefore we had need be circumſpect. [ver. 13. and for this cauſe.] Now followeth the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding of the alarum a ſecond time by the Apoſtle to vs, the vſe of all this great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the povver of darknes: which though for
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17283:56"/> ſubſtance it is all one vvith verſe 11, yet the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in it are divers: for the holy Ghoſt doth in repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons inforce circumſtances different; both for our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delight and inſtruction, as the ſame meat maketh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers diſhes if diverſly coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. The words are plaine, the parts are the exhortation to our duty (grounded on the vvords before) and the ends of our duty: he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the one, leading to the other. Firſt, reſiſtance amplified from the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of time, in the evill day; that is, in the houres of temptation, of afflictions, of the power of darknes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, perſeuerance, ſet down by the antecedent,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:17283:56"/> That hauing finiſhed all things (that is, hauing out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wreſtled all the euills which meete you in theſe hard times) you may bee able to holde your owne; yea to go on more and more ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hened and fuller of reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then before. Wee ſee then what is the end of all that is reuealed of euill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, their ſubtiltie and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; That we pull vp good hearts to reſiſt them. It is not to feed curioſity, but to make vs more vigilant. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. Be ſober &amp; watch, for your aduerſary the Diuel goes about as a roaring Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c. Much leſſe is it the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of <hi>Paul</hi> to disharten vs, as thoſe naughty Spies, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 13. who tolde of the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:17283:57"/> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo as to quaile the courage of the Iſraelites: but this faithfull ſeruant doth ſo tell them, that hee may whet vp our ſpirits to the reſiſtance of them. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.9. Whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in the faith. This then muſt be our care, when we know how power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſubtill aduerſaries wee haue, To buckle our ſelues to battell, and gird vp our loynes to martial reſiſtance. <hi>Now, that we may bee encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to wage this warre, who are ſo weake,</hi> Firſt, we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſpirit in vs, is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then the ſpirite in the world. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.4. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which doth beare at one end of the ſtaffe in euery godly fight, is ſtronger then
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17283:57"/> all the Diuels in hell. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, all the Diuels power is limited, and that ſhort, that he is not able to wound vs mortally. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 15. Hee ſhall bruſe thy heele: he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wound vs in the head, or hurt vs, as Chriſt doth him (yea and maketh vs likewiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) when he doth tread him vnder our feete. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16 20. The God of peace ſhall ſhortly tread down Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, &amp;c. All his power is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued and lymited: hee can not touch a cattell that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to vs, nor a hogge, if Chriſt doe not make him his warrant.</p>
            <p>This we may ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, what is the cauſe, when wee are in the beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, the Diuell doth bring
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17283:58"/> vs downe and moyle vs in ſinne; and yet, when by ſin wee lie vnder him, hee can do nothing till we are riſen by dayly repentance: hee is at his chaines end, and can goe no further: if we were in the mouth of this roring Lion, hee could not couch his fangs without Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his power, hee can doe nothing with vs but by our owne leaue, hee hee muſt knock and ask our leaue before he enter. Now a tyrant that raignes by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie, is not much feared: and an enemy <hi>Qui non poteſt vincere, niſi volentem,</hi> is not much dreadfull. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, Chriſt hath vnarmed, and bound him. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.15. and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17283:58"/> hath ſpoyled the principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Panoplia</hi> is gone. Now for a man in compleat har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to feare a naked bound Gyant, were too much da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardiſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, We haue the good Angels with vs, fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 91.11. For he ſhall giue his Angels charge ouer thee, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.14. Are they not all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſpirits ſent forth to miniſter for their ſakes, which ſhall be heires of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? So that if our eyes were opened, vve might ſee (as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaide) there are more with vs, then againſt vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, our Captaine, the Lord Ieſus, the Lord of Hoſtes, the Firſt &amp; the Laſt, is with vs for our encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:17283:59"/> If one <hi>Ioſuah</hi> could ſtand againſt one and thirtie Kings, of <hi>Canaan,</hi> what principalities, powers, vertues, ſhall be able to ſtand before our <hi>Iehoſhuah,</hi> the Lord of Hoaſts? Wherefore though they be mighty, yet we may ſay as he, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.9. They are as bread for vs, &amp; let vs take heed how we let our hearts be daunted, &amp; ſpeake of our ſinnes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch infirmities, as if we neuer ſhold out-grow them, and wiſh our ſelues dead, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſo yoaked. For if God would take vs at our wordes, it were enough to keepe vs out of that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſt of his. <hi>Num.</hi> 14.28. As I liue ſaith the Lord, I will doe vnto you euen as
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17283:59"/> yee haue ſpoken in mine eares. <hi>But we ſerue a gracious Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> The ſecond thing to bee marked, is, <hi>We must prepare our ſelues before the day of temptation commeth.</hi> Take vp, that when it commeth you may reſiſt. It is good for vs to be appointed aforehand, when we know that we ſhal be ſet vpon with euills. <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.25. Hee when it was faire weather looked for a ſeaſon of temptations. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20.24. hee cared for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but this, that he might finiſh his courſe with ioy, ſhoot the vp-ſhot well, and in the euill time ſurrender a comfortable ſpirit to his Creator. And this duty is enioyned, when wee are bid
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17283:60"/> be ſober and watchfull. For firſt, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> in preparing to warre, is the continuance of peace. If a nation grow ſecure, and let fall the care of all warlike munitions, it is a whiſtle that calleth, vpon them, ſom forrain enemy: when men goe naked it maketh knaues ſet vpon them, that would not ſtirre were they weapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, wee cannot diſpatch ſmal things to com off happily, without proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence before they come: If one put off things to the point of time in which they are to bee vſed, how many difficulties doe they meete with, which with forecaſt are happily contriued? As it fared with thoſe Virgins <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. who brought not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17283:60"/> oyle, till their Lord was come: they then came too late, the day after the Fair: ſo a thouſand to one, that who neglecteth the preſent time, and prouideth not, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer in the euill day bee able to compaſſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This then rebuketh the way of many, who take no care for the time to come, let to morrw care for it ſelfe; who may be ſent to School to the Ant, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.6.8. ſhee doth in ſummer ſtore vp for winter; who may bee chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by their owne courſes in things earthly. If they haue a iourney to make of pleaſure, they will be weeks aforehand prouiding for it: if they feare hard times, they will lay vp ſomething
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17283:61"/> againſt the dear year. Which wiſedome in earthly things may euince their folly, who wil not get a ſtock of grace, on which to ſpend in hard times, when it is no eaſie gathering. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it muſt teach vs to haue our eyes in our head: and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing, euill times are to come, let vs hide our ſelues vnder the wings of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. Let this this be one of our petitions, That we may finde grace from the throne of grace, in the times of need. In <hi>Anno</hi> 88. when vve had intelligence of the the ſhips comming againſt vs, the Drum was ſtricken vp in our ſtreets, preſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney walking, muſtering e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vvhere, all kinde of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17283:61"/> prouiſion, that wee might be able to meet them victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly: ſo it becometh, that hauing certain intelligence, that theſe times will come, though it is vncertaine when, wee ſhould put our ſelues alwayes in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is to bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, <hi>That when hee biddeth all the faithfull prouide againſt the euill day, hee taketh this for granted, tho whoſoeuer are the Lords, in this courſe of their liues ſhall know ſome hard ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> Hee doth not ſhoot off falſe fires, making them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of moon-ſhine in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but forewarneth them of that which ſhould befall them. Neither doth hee tell them of euill times, on this
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17283:62"/> particular ground, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions were hard at hand only, which are not alwaies; but on this ground, that the powers of darkneſſe doe fights againſt vs, which is common to all ages. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the doctrine is plaine, that the Lords ſhall knowe in the courſe of their liues, ſom times full of difficulty. We muſt not think that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moones will laſt all the year. True it is, there is great diuerſitie: yet this alſo is true, that in all liues they haue their euill dayes in them. Some are very drip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping euer and anon ſhowrs, like <hi>Iacobs:</hi> ſome faire in the fore-part, and ending, but hauing a ſound ſhower at noon-time, like <hi>Iob:</hi> ſom
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:17283:62"/> in the ending clowdy and ſtormy, as <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.18. It is ſaid of <hi>Peter,</hi> that when he was young, hee went whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee would, &amp;c. when theſe days ſhal com it is hid. <hi>Iob</hi> 24.1, How ſhould not the times bee hidden from the Almighty, ſeeing who know him, ſee not his daies. But that ſuch doe abide vs is reuealed. Euery one that will liue godly, muſt ſuffer perſecution. Wee muſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogh many afflictions, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. If wee haue not our chaſtiſing wee are baſtards, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This then doth check the ſecurity of many, who becauſe it is, and hath been well, they thinke the hand of the Almighty will neuer alter: think they ſhall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17283:63"/> die on their neſts. <hi>Iob</hi> 29.18. Then I ſayd, I ſhall die in my neſt, I ſhall multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie my dayes as the ſand; thinke they ſhall neuer bee moued, neuer ſee euill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.6. That their mount ſhall not be ſhaken. They might as well ſay, the ſunne ſhines, they ſhall neuer ſee raine againe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, we muſt learne to walke in fear. The more proſperous our eſtate is, the more we muſt feare. We are ſure to knowe euill times, ſooner or later: ſuppoſe thou ſhouldeſt eſcape till death, it wil be an euill hower. For looke as enemies beſieging a place, if ſome come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue them, they will deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perately make on-ſet, as
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17283:63"/> knovving, that if they vvin it not preſently, they ſhall never prevaile: ſo Satan in death, then or never muſt he get the day of thee. Thinke therefore hovv furiouſly hee vvill aſſault: feare therefore thoſe times; and the rather, becauſe if you fear, and your hearts melt; God wil be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull. As <hi>Ioſias</hi> vvhen his heart melted at Gods threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, God tould him, they ſhould not come to paſſe in his daies. If a rod ſhaken be enough, a parent vvill not ſtrike vvith it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that hee ſaith, having finiſhed all things, that is, outwraſtled all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils wherwith in thoſe hard times you ſhall be exerciſed; obſerue hence, that <hi>when
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17283:64"/> times of temptation come, wee muſt look for many things wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee are to bee tryed.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Having finiſhed all things, wee muſt not looke to haue done: when ſome one trouble is outwraſtled, one woe paſt, two follow, aſwell in perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall as publike viſitations, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Iob</hi> when GOD brought the euill dayes on him, how many things, one in the neck of another, did exerciſe him? changes, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of ſorrow did beſet him, <hi>Iob</hi> 10.17. Wherefore broughteſt thou mee out of the wombe? oh that I had periſhed, and no eie had ſeen me. So Chriſt: the divell came to him with a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould temptation, and then gaue back but for a ſeaſon.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17283:64"/> The particular evill day is deſcribed thus, <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> 12.2. that after raine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth clouds: that is, it is like this April-weather, as one ſhower is vnburdened, another is brewed: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as in the euill day, when GOD doth muſter his iudgements againſt the wicked, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, God hath a pit, ſnare, feare; as <hi>Eſay</hi> 24.17.</p>
            <p>Or as <hi>Amos</hi> 5.19. as if a man did flee from a Lyon, and a Beare meet him; or went into the houſe, and leaned his hand on the wall, and a ſerpent bit him; that is, hee hath one euill in the necke of another to deſtroy them: ſo in the day of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hee hath many exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, that his children may
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17283:65"/> bee throughly tryed, as gold in the furnace. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Therefore men muſt not thinke, when one euill is paſt, all their bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe is ouer; as children, if they haue had their pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thinke all ſure for a time after: neither yet muſt wee bee ſo ſhort of ſpirit, as to wexe weary when God dealeth with vs, though wee like weather-beaten birds would ſun our wings quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for, vvee are all like <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim, Hoſ.</hi> 10.11. vvee loue to threſh, but endure not the yoak eaſily. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Again, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many trials in our euill dayes which abide vs, vvee haue need to begge at Gods hand, that hee would teach vs to deny our ſelves, that he would ſtrengthen vs in the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17283:65"/> inner man, to all long-ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with ioyfulnes. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> vvee muſt learne to rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon on the vvorſt: the beſt vvill ſaue it ſelfe. It is good to thinke; I ſee vvhere the hand of God hath begunne vvith mee, I knovve not vvhere it vvill end vvith me. Caſt the vvorſt; Short ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting heere may loſe all. That is a vvorthy reſolution of <hi>Iob</hi> in his day, 13.15. If thou vvilt kill me, yet vvill I truſt in thee. Hee that beleeueth, maketh not haſte.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Laſtly vvee ſee, that <hi>Wee muſt not onely haue care to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraſtle euils for the preſent, but to perſeuere after; that is, hold our owne in grace, yea haue grace increaſed; ſhewing it ſelf in a holy defiance of all enmity,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17283:66"/> if the houre of death be at hand: or in further reſolution to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter new enmities, if life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue.</hi> Wee faint not, ſaith the Apoſtle, nay vvee are more then conquerers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. Heereto muſt bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called the glorious exulting, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. I am perſvvaded, that neither life, nor death, &amp;c. I haue fought a fight, vvhat is laid vp for me but a crovvne of righteouſneſſe? And vvhile life continueth, vvee muſt bee ſtrengthened for further reſiſtance. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10, And the God of all grace, vvhich hath called vs to his eternall glory by Ieſus Chriſt, after that yee haue ſuffred a little, make you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, confirme, ſtrengthen, and ſtabliſh you; Where, he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17283:66"/> maketh our confirming and ſtrengthening of vs, a fruit follovving our ſubduing of temptations: as trees ſhaken, root more firmly; and cities beſieged, vvhen the enemie prevaileth not, they grovve euer after more invincible.</p>
            <p>This then muſt teach vs, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> vvho haue endured many things, vvee muſt haue care ſtill to perſeuere. What vvould be more pitiful then to ſee a ſhip, having paſſed all the billovves of the ſea, runne vpon rockes in the mouth of the hauen? ſo vvhen vvee haue paſſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſurges in this vvorld, and novv ſhould come into the hauen; then, not to go on, and caſt our anchor in a ſafe road, vvere too too pittifull.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17283:67"/> Againe, marke vvhat minde vvee ſhould haue to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, that haue ſuffered; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, vvhen vve giue ouer to endure, all our former ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is in vaine. Novv if a man had laid much money forth on a thing, vvould hee loſe his former charge for a trifle? no; he vvould rather double the coſt hee had been at: for, we muſt carry minds rather to double all our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, then to giue ouer before our end. Againe, the more we haue gon through, the more the Lord giueth vs theſe mindes; the more vvee ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be fleſhed againſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſſaults. Many faile in this: the ſtanding after many trials haue beene vvell endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as <hi>Dauid</hi> fought all the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17283:67"/> Lords battels, and paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay his daies happily, yet aftervvard fell moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now follow the ſeverall pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of armour, of which in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall two things muſt be marked;</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that vve muſt not ſo preciſely difference theſe things, as to think that one may not ſerue for the vſe of another, as that the ſhield may not doo in ſome ſort what the breaſt-plate doth: for; 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth faith a breaſt-plate. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> for the diſtinction of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiue and offenſiue armor, the truth is, that though ſom part may with more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and emine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy be tearmed offenſiue: yet they are al ſuch weapons as doo ſtrike down
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17283:68"/> aduerſary power, aſwell as ward the blowes which the diuell reacheth vs. Faith therefore is called our victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4. This is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory that ouercometh the world, euen our faith. Now then to conſider of the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts as they be in order, Firſt he ſaith, Stand, beeing girded about with the gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of truth. For the maner of proceeding, <hi>before we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the doctrines and word of exhortation, we will ſeek out foure things:</hi> firſt, what is meant by euery one: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what is the vſe of it: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how the diuell doth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to diſarme vs of it: fourthly, how we may hold our owne againſt him. The girdle of truth then cometh
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17283:68"/> firſt: Now truth ſomtime ſignifieth the doctrine of truth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.17. But that it cannot heere ſignifie; the ſword of the ſpirit, beeing thus to bee conſidered. Truth therefore heere, is ſoundneſſe: which is alwaies accompanied with conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, For which cauſe the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes doe in one word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie both.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond, <hi>this gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle hath three vſes.</hi> Firſt, it doth adorn vs: for this was the vſe of the <hi>Studded belt,</hi> which the ſouldiers did weare, to hide the gaping ioynts of their armour, which would haue been vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely: and nothing doth adorne a ſoule more, then vprightneſſe: as our Sauiour
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17283:69"/> commending <hi>Nathanael,</hi> gaue out this ſpeech of him; Beholde a true Iſraelite in whom there is no guile, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.47.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a girdle doth tie other cloathes about vs, cloſe to vs, which otherwiſe the winde would blowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and would hang but looſe vpon vs: ſo this gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of truth doth containe and holde together all other graces, wherewith the ſoule is arrayed; and without truth to keepe them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in time all of them are borne away with winds of temptation. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20.21. That grace that was not knit together with honeſty of heart, came to nothing in the end: as appears in the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17283:69"/> Parable.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a girdle truſſing vp the loynes of a man mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately, doth ſtrengthen a man; whence is the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſo often vſed of gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp the loynes: ſo this grace addeth great ſtrength to the inner man, as wee may ſee in <hi>Iob;</hi> who when God ſeemed, and men did fight againſt him, when hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; earth ſeemed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt him, yet this did ſtick by him, Chap. 27.5, Vntill I die, I will neuer take away mine innocency from my ſelfe. Now the works of it are exerciſed in our daily courſe, or in the evill times of greater exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe then ordinary. Dayly it doth make vs ſtrike at the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17283:70"/> roots of hypocriſie, we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne in vs, and reſiſt the temptations of the Diuell, which tend to make vs cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in their end, or manner of pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>formance: but eſpecially it doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs in the euil time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Diuell ſhall bee ready to bear vs down, that we haue been but hypocrites. Now for the third thing, <hi>The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doth by foure meanes eſpecially ſeeks to wipe vs of this girdle.</hi> He will from the example of others,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> reaſon thus: Such, &amp; ſuch as <hi>Iudas,</hi> haue had grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things then you, and gone further then you, yet they were but hypocrites, How canſt thou tell? is it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe with thee? Many firſt are laſt, &amp;c. <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wee
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17283:70"/> muſt auoide this obiection, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>by learning to diſtinguiſh true conſtant grace, from fained and and temporary: which is fitly done by theſe two differences.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, the wicked haue ſtreames of graces often, but they haue no communion with Chriſt as the godly haue; and therefore their graces wither when heate commeth. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. It is a true liuing faith that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Chriſt to dwell in the heart, and this is the cauſe why our grace laſteth: as wee finde by dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ebbes. And this water runneth exceedng lowe: yet hauing the well-head in vs, and renewing our faith on him the quickning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, riuers doe afreſh runne
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17283:71"/> out of our bellies, and the current of grace as high as before. The temporiſer, though he haue a ſtreame of grace, yet wanting the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to feed it, it muſt needs dry away; as thoſe ſtreames, or ponds which haue no ſpring, nor head of water to maintaine them, cannot continue. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, theſe hypocrites receiue the grace they haue, retayning ſome notorious ſinne, or courſe in leſſer euils, wherein they hate reformation: as <hi>Herod, Mat.</hi> 8. Now this maketh grace it cannot be held with them. For as a ſtomack ill affected thorough choler, though neuer ſo wholeſom meats bee receiued into it, yet it cannot holde them,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17283:71"/> but is prouoked to caſt: ſo where there is this obſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule, the wilfull loue of any ſinfull courſe, whatſoeuer grace is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into the heart, it will not let it reſt, but maketh the ſoule caſt it vp vpon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Diuell will from our vnſound perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duties thus reaſon againſt vs: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Thou knoweſt thou haſt often looked more at man then God, and haſt propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded indirect means when thou ſhouldeſt haue eyed his glory onely: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou haſt not this truth. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> We muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh of hypocriſie, as of other ſinnes: for as ſinne is raigning, or not; ſo is hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17283:72"/> Now there may be this, not raigning hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in the hearts and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Gods people. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Pſal.</hi> 31. when hee ſaid, Bleſſed is hee, in whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit there is no guile, did take him ſelfe tardy in this evill: and <hi>Bradford,</hi> with other of thoſe moſt holy Martyrs, doe much ſeeke pardon of hypocriſie and carnall goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling: but no ſinne that raigneth not, muſt diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage vs. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> How may we know it raigneth not? <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> If we haue purpoſe againſt it. Secondly, if we haue griefe for it. Thirdly, if we ſeeke for ſtrength againſt it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note>Thirdly, the Diuell will through croſſes wee beare, and from the preiudicate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17283:72"/> of other men beare vs downe that vvee are not ſound hearted. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The book of <hi>Iob</hi> is but a canuaſe about this; where it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that no calamities can proue a man an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, nor no opinion of men, though wiſe and holy: The ſelfe ſame thing befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him that ſweareth, and him that feareth an oath. <hi>Eccl ſ.</hi> 9 1 2.</p>
            <p>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tly, the Diuell will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to foiſt in this leauen of hypocriſie in our dayly courſe, that thus by little &amp; little, hee may picke this good ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of righteouſneſſe out of our hearts. Here our reſiſtance is to holde vs to our owne, and pray to God to rebuke him. And this
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17283:73"/> way is made for the fourth queſtion, <hi>How we may keepe this truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, by conſidering the woefull curſe that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the contrary: For God deteſteth nothing ſo, as hypocriſie: and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth thoſe duties that are not done to him in ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. 2. The bleſſedneſſe of it. Bleſſed is hee whoſe heart is vpright, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. it is the delight of God; and hither belong all the vſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue named. 3. In our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon daily duties to labour this: 1. To performe them with our heart. 2. As in the ſight of God. 3. To his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for this will make the grace of truth to be deepely rooted in vs.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:17283:73"/>
            <p>Now the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the Doctrin, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> and Vſe; this is it that wee are taught: <hi>That we muſt get vprightneſſe of heart for the ſtrengthning of vs. Luke</hi> 12.35, Let your loynes alſo be girded about. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, Gird vp the loynes of your minde. Now this is the chief girdle that adorneth vs, keepes all our cloathes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſtrengthens the loins of vs: thus <hi>Dauid</hi> girded him ſelfe, I will walke in the vprightneſſe of my heart, in the midſt of my houſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 20.3. <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, For our reioycing is this, the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicitie and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pureneſſe, &amp; not in fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſedome, but by the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17283:74"/> grace of God: we haue had our conuerſation in the world, and moſt of all to you wards: and it muſt not bee a naturall truth which may cauſe men to hate hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with their own know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but hath a fruit of the ſpirit: ſuch as muſt make vs not only look to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward dutie, but to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard performance of it; ſuch as muſt make vs ſeeke to glorifie God. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Therefore, ſuch as walke onely, giving their outward man in an outward co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formity to God, they bee counterfeits, and ſlippes in religion: ſuch as, whoſe righteouſneſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth like a tertian Ague, &amp; is as a morning deaw; theſe are vvithout this girdle: and
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17283:74"/> a man may bee bolde to ſay here, as to childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Not girt, not bleſſed: but many that haue girdles, yet keep them ſluttiſhly: who are here like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to bee reprooued; and fewe of vs can waſh our hands, we being all hollow peeces, if due examination be taken. <hi>Conſider but theſe foure things, and you ſhall bee better able to ferret out the guile of your ſpirits.</hi> Firſt, how careleſſe vve are of the ſpirituall action, in thoſe things we perform: as in praier. To the ſpiritual do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this dutie, is required, firſt, preparation, or keeping the heart fit for it. 2. A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout inward deſire, groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to God. 3. An away<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, after we haue done, to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17283:75"/> ſee how God anſwereth vs. But who doth not lightly paſſe ouer theſe duties? which is no better then a vviping the out ſide of the diſh, not looking to that vvithin. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Mark, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of ſin, we more are ſorry, &amp; deale againſt this or that branch of corruption, which ſhooteth out to our diſgrace, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the root it ſelfe. Now <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. in <hi>Paul</hi> we ſee, the law of euil, which did dwell within him, was his principall matter of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Marke the courſe of our affections, and wee ſhall ſee how vnſound wee are towards God. If a thing touch our ſelues, our blood will quickly be in our nails: if a man doe knowe this or
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17283:75"/> that by vs amiſſe, it is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, the ſhame of it much vpbraids vs: but things that offend God, and vvhich vve knovve hee ſeeth amiſſe in vs, vve can let theſe paſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing affected; a ſigne, our loue to him is not ſo ſound; our feare of him, and deſire of praiſe vvith him, not ſo vnfained.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> let vs obſerue how frequently our actions are corrupted. As, ſometime wee vndertake to deale for ſome that ſpeaketh to vs, but doo it without any hearty well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhing to him; ſometime not ſticking to ſay to our friend, I muſt ſpeake to you for faſhion, but doo as you pleaſe: wee viſit ſicke ones, but not ſtirring vp our bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:17283:76"/> of mercy, wee ſpeake a great many phraſes of courſe, our conſcience tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs it is otherwiſe. So is our behaviour: wee make a ſemblance of reverence, but how far it is from the heart, this may teſtifie; that we can (abſent from the parties) vſe their names proverbially, we ſhal not haue ſuch a one breake into ſiniſter ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if the fift &amp; ſixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements were blankes with vs. So in fruits of loue: wee can do this party good ſometime, but it is to keepe another vnder, who would elſe ſprout forth ſo far, that his ſhade would dimme our lights: as, I will doo for ſuch a one, they knowe good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, they will do their
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17283:76"/> homage, ſuch a one will thanke mee for it, I am ſure it will not bee giuen cleane away. In leaving ſin, many leaue it not becauſe they hate it as ſin, but it hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten broken out to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; which is more, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their owne ſinnes, not deſiring to giue glory to God, and gaine a teſtimony of a ſound heart; but becauſe worldly wiſdome doth tell them, It is the beſt for them to tell their owne tale, or it were double folly to make dainty of that all the world knoweth. Thus in taking vp good duties as orders in our family, many often look not ſo much at the conſcience of Gods commandement as at this; The eyes of men are
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17283:77"/> vpon vs, all the world vvill cry ſhame, if ſuch things bee neglected altogether. But you that wil keep truth, take heed of this haulting: for though there may bee ſome reliques of hypocriſie in a good man, yet the nature of haulting is, it will goe quite out of the way if it bee not heald. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.13, And make ſtraight ſteps vnto your feet, leſt that which is haulting be turned out of the way. And hee that limpeth thus ſtill, may haue a lame leg by it to his graue. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, vvee muſt ſtirre vp our ſelues to keepe this girdle cloſe to vs, which is of ſuch excellent vſe: this is wouen in heauen, no ſhop can ſerue you vvith this, but that onely. Wee
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17283:77"/> buy vs girdles for the body; and if coſtly ones, vvee keep them carefully, O bee vviſe for your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Novv follovveth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of our furniture; Hauing put on the breaſt-plate of righteouſnes. To fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv the ſelf ſame order: firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for that vvhich is meant heere, there is a threefould righteouſnes. One imputed by faith, but this can not bee mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for this is the ſhield of faith. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Another righteouſnes inherent in vs, vvhich is part of the divine quality be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in vs, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, a righteouſnes of courſe, or converſation, or vvorke: thus the thing don is called righteouſnes. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.7, He that doth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:17283:78"/> is righteous. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.3. Riches and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſhall be in his houſe, and his righteouſnes endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for euer. Novv the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is not ſo fitly meant heere, becauſe the Apoſtle bringeth in the nevv crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture armed: therefore it is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to diſtinguiſh him from his armour. Neither is truth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the nevv creature, but the quality of him: neither is faith and loue, properly taken in their differences, the nevv creature: for they ſhall ceaſe. Though there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I vvill not ſtriue againſt it, yet <hi>I take the righteouſnes of the courſe and converſation, heere principally to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. Now into this part of our furniture, three pares are
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:17283:78"/> enfoulded: for this righteouſnes hath theſe three branches:</hi> Firſt, for the time paſt, a teſtimony excuſing vs, vvhich is the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12, For our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing is this, the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our conſcience, &amp;c. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for the time to come, a purpoſe to auoid all euil, and to do that is good. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Antiochians vvith purpoſe of heart to cleaue vnto the Lord. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> in reſpect of our daily vveaknes, vvhich doth dint and bruiſe this breaſt plate, there muſt bee ſorrovv and humble confeſſion of ſinne, vvith ſeeking pardon: this doth beat it forth ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine, &amp; vnderline it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that it is as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17283:79"/> to vs as euer. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs (vvee ſay) daily our treſpaſſes: for, our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes is rather in purpoſe then performance, rather in confeſſion of imperfection, then in any perfection vvee can attaine. Secondly, for the vſe of this: it is daily, or more extraordinary: the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe is this, that vvhen the diuell doth tempt vs to ſin, if the breaſt be couered with this purpoſe not to offend, then his ſuggeſtions will fall downe like paper-ſhot, and ſhall not pearce vs. How can I doo this great wickedneſſe, and ſo ſinne againſt God? The more extraordinary, when men ſhal load vs with preiudicate opinions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning vs: this will beare
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17283:79"/> it off; I know nothing by my ſelfe, I care not for mans iudgement, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3. As touching mee, I paſſe very little to bee iudged by you. When the divell telleth vs, Thou art not elected, thou haſt no faith, thou art not ſanctified, all doth come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes; this confirmeth to vs our election. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, Wherefore brethren, giue rather diligence to make your calling and election ſure. This aſſureth vs that vvee are iuſt, our ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, and vvee ſanctified. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.7, He that doth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, is righteous.</p>
            <p>The more beneficiall it is, the more ſtudious Satan is to diſarme vs of it. Firſt
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17283:80"/> therefore, <hi>the Diuell will keep vs from getting this, in this manner:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> What doe you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take you to ſuch care of your life? God is mercifull, Chriſt hath dyed to redeem you, hee vvill not loſe what hee hath bought ſo deare. <hi>Anſw. </hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> God is mercifull to them that feare him, Chriſt redeemeth thoſe whom hee ſanctifieth, to be a peculiar people vnto him, zealous of good workes. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.14, Who gaue himſelfe for vs, that hee might redeeme vs from all iniquity, and purge vs to be a peculiar people to himſelfe, zealous of good workes. If wee will haue ſome kinde of righteouſnes, hee will perſwade vs to ſuch a kinde of breaſt-plate, as is
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:17283:80"/> not of a right metall: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> that is, a generall profeſſion, and an honeſt carriage, in this manner; Though it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite you ſhould haue all righteouſneſſe: yet what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all this, adoe? God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth you as a father ſpareth his children. All the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God are holy, it is not for righteouſneſſe you ſhall be ſaued. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Wee muſt haue ſound righteouſneſſe, and endeuour of perfection. If your righteouſneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, yee ſhall not enter into the kingdome of heauen, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20. Though Iſrael bee as the ſand of the Sea, yet a remnant only ſhall be ſaued. Not all that ſay Lord, Lord,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17283:81"/> ſhall enter into the kingdom of heauen. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. Bee yee perfect, as your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heauen is perfect. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2. Deſire and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to follow after it. 3. If wee vvill enter it, hee will breake vs off by difficulties, diſcomforts, diſtractions, and make vs yeeld our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, as wearie. But heere the power of Chriſt, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour and finiſher of faith, the beginner &amp; perfecter of his owne good work, doth carry vs on: and the ſeed of God is of ſuch force, that it will not let vs fall to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Secondly, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on one hand, and the comfort of his acceptance on the other ſide, do encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:17283:81"/> vs: ſo that this aſſault is fruſtrate. 4. He ſheweth himſelfe a Diuell indeed; and by aggrauating our imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, will offer to wreſt from vs the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, in this wiſe. Gods eye is too pure to beholde any euill, thou ſhouldeſt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, &amp;c. But thy beſt deeds haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ſprinkled with filthineſſe, thy owne conſcience hath condemned thee in them; God is greater then thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The anſwer is, by getting a ſound knowledge how farre vvee are to ſtand vpon the righteouſneſſe of our courſes; of which mark theſe things. Firſt, wee doe not account of it as able to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17283:82"/> abide the tryall of iuſtice, or to ſtand for our full righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe before God. This wee account is droſſe and dung; theſe things may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may a Papiſt, they cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſmay vs. 2. We place the ſtrength of our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in two things. 1. That it doth teſtifie of our true faith: for a worke good in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y meaſure, doth argue a heart good in ſom meaſure; for you cannot haue a figge of a thiſtle: now a heart in any meaſure good, doth ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue a true faith, for that on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly can purifie the heart. 2. In this that wee know they are pleaſing vnto our God: not that they can endure the tryall of his iuſtice in themſelues, but becauſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:17283:82"/> on Chriſt doth couer their imperfections: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are iuſtly accepted tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough grace, when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is couered; they being not ſo much ours, as the worke of the ſpirit (<hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.11. ſtrengthened with all might through his power vnto all patience, &amp;c.) the wants ſet aſide.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now wee ſhall ſtrongly holde this part of our armour, if we exerciſe theſe things.</hi> 1. Labor to giue obedience of faith, in the leaſt things: for there muſt be preciſeneſſe in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, &amp; we muſt count nothing little that he commandeth. <hi>Salomon</hi> will haue vs keepe his precepts as the ſight of our eye. <hi>Pro.</hi> 7.2.</p>
            <pb n="158" facs="tcp:17283:83"/>
            <p>And little ſinnes liued in will make way to greater. Men growe from ſtealing pinnes, to points, from points to pounds. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Wee muſt renew dayly a ſorrow for our ordinary and ſmaller offences: for though it bee the weakeneſſe of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, that is able to beare with nothing that is a little offenſiue to it; yet it is a bleſſed frame of the ſoule, when it cannot digeſt the leaſt ſinne, but is ready to turne at it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. Wee muſt think what ſecure and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable courſes wee haue, while we keep this purpoſe, and practice of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and what a bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it is, when wee haue our conſciences accuſing
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:17283:83"/> for any more grieuous ſweruing, the beſt is when it commeth home by weeping croſſe: but how wofull is the ſtate of the ſoule, till re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance be giuen? For as a ſtomack ſurcharged, which hath neither vent vpward nor downward, ſo is a ſoule clogged with guilt, but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting repentance. Now then to ſpeake to the doctrine: we that are Chriſtians, muſt all labour to ſtrengthen our ſelues with the teſtimony of a good conſcience, and a righteous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation. Thus <hi>Hezechiah</hi> vvalked, dooing that which was good in the ſight of God, neither tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on right hand, nor left, from all that God had commanded. Thus <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:17283:84"/> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> walked, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.6. But we haue <hi>Paul</hi> by precept and practice, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the point. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8, Furthermore brethren, what ſoeuer things are honeſt, whatſoeuer things are iuſt, whatſoeuer things are pure, &amp;c. thinke on theſe things. And we may ſee, firſt, how his conſcience did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him for time preſent. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3, As touching me I paſſe little to bee iudged of you. How he endeauoured for the time to come to keep it ſo. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.16, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I endeauour alwaies, to haue a cleere conſcience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, and towards man. 3. That hee was not without his exerciſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Oh miſerable man
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:17283:84"/> that I am, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. This will keep vs in our daily courſe, and in the euill houre; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if theſe bee not renewed, wee ſhall come by ſcare: as <hi>Iudah</hi> going foorth without harneſſing himſelfe, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing this purpoſe, we ſee how ſoon he was wounded with euill. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dutie of Chriſtians, doth rebuke ſuch, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther content themſelues with a falſe armour, or haue none at all. Some there are, that are good Church men, honeſt, righteous, iuſt dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling men; but becauſe they lay not a good foundation of faith in Ieſus Chriſt, and of repentance from dead works, becauſe they care not for the ſpirit and power of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:17283:85"/> godlineſſe: therfore, brown paper ſhall as well keepe out Musket ſhotte, as this vvill helpe them, when the Diuel ſhall let fly his murdring bullets. Many haue none at all, but naked breaſts ſhot through already, their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience being able to accuſe them, that they haue liued in profanenes, contempt of Gods ordinances, in pride, vvrath, couetouſneſſe, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: their purpoſes haue beene to walke after their owne hearts luſts, dooing that which is good in their owne eyes. In ſteed of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe neuer to be repented of, they can tell you, they vvere at ſuch a place, where they vvere frolick, had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment with ſports, &amp;c.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:17283:85"/> Poore thralls of the Diuell that haue no armor of God vpon them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> 2. Wee muſt learne our dutie, not to run on at aduenture, but looke to theſe rules: wee are all Prieſts of God, we muſt not goe without this breſt-plate enameled with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim</hi> and <hi>Thummin.</hi> Wherefore looke that our conſciences ſpeake with vs, God is greater then they, renew your purpoſes euery day, ſtrike ſure coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants with God: take vp the bleſſed exerciſe of broken hearts, bewaile your dayly vvants: for wee ſhould not let a thought which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wry, no not a dream, which ſauoureth corruption, paſſe without a cenſure. <hi>Iob</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſanctified his houſhold
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:17283:86"/> on ſuſpicion, and iealouſie, then neglected matters al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready apparantly euill.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the third, which anſwereth to the greaues, or legge-harneſſe, [and your feet ſhod] 1. For the meaning: Some doe conſtrue the preaching of the Goſpell of peace, the readineſſe to confeſſion; but this is rather a fruit of our being ſhod, then the ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf. And this is a more particular thing, as which agreeth with times of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, and perſons called to make confeſſion. But all the parts of this armour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to all times, and to all perſons. The ſenſe is; being ſhod with ſuch furniture, as the Goſpell of peace doth
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:17283:86"/> help vs to.</p>
            <p>Now the goſpell of peace doth tell vs two things, that make vs fully appointed for all aduerſities; that God is through Chriſt a mercifull Father: for, all enmity is killed in his Croſſe. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it doth aſſure vs, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that can befall is made for vs 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.23, Whether they be things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or things to come, all are yours, and ye Chriſts, &amp; Chriſt Gods. Not life onely, but death is ours; that is, is made to ſerue for our good. So the ſoule, knowing theſe things, is harneſſed to goe in the waies of tribulation. Secondly for the vſe: it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in vndergoing our d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afflictions: for, euery da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:17283:87"/> hath his miſery. Secondly, in paſſing theſe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry euils which ſhall betide vs: through many afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wee muſt looke to enter into the kingdome of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22: as the vſe of boots and greaues is againſt all roughneſſe of the vvay, that wee may tread on flinty paths, or thornes, and that without taking hurt. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Now the diuell will firſt labour to keepe vs from ſeeking after this peace,</hi> by lulling vs aſleepe with a falſe peace, as this; If God did not loue thee, thou ſhouldeſt not thus proſper, thou haſt no troubles, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but peace ſhall follow thee. But <hi>wee must learne to distinguiſh betweene a true and falſe peace.</hi> Firſt, this is grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:17283:87"/> on no outward thing, but on forgiueneſſe of ſinne. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, Then beeing iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith, wee haue peace towards God through Ieſus Chriſt: this is brought to vs, and applied by the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, by praier, the goſpell of peace, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6, Be nothing carefull, but in all things let your requeſts be ſhewed to God, in praier and ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now, the worldlings peace is ſo much the greater, the leſſe the goſpell is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to him: for, this light will not let him ſleepe; and for wading to it by prayer, by beleeving the mercy of God, and promiſe that all things ſhall worke for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good, he knoweth not wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe things meane. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:17283:88"/> the divell will tell vs that haue our part in this peace, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> There is no peace to the wicked, <hi>Eſay</hi> 48. <hi>vlt.</hi> Thou haſt much wickednes which God cannot but hate. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The wicked, who is not iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified through faith, canne haue no peace: but Chriſt hath covered mine imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver kneweſt what trouble meant, till thou cameſt to this goſpel: Since, thy own heart, men, ſpirituall vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes, thine own friends haue hated thee. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2. They ſhal excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate you, &amp;c. this peace ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with all kinde of diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. As the weather frie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing neuer ſo aegrely, a man well booted and appointed
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:17283:88"/> in that kinde, may ride as warme as wooll: ſo a man ſhod with this, may be quiet in the midſt of diſquietnes: for, this is his peace; in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing our mindes prepared with knowledge of our peace which the goſpell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealeth: not that he ſhal not haue euill many waies, but that Gods mercy ſhall not be taken from him, and that all of them ſhall work together to his good. Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan will ſay; God is angry with you, which the effects doo teſtifie. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> By diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing anger as thus, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and loue ſtand together in parents, the more they loue, the more they are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the dangerous courſes of their children: Therfore
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:17283:89"/> it followeth not, God is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, therfore he loueth thee not, therefore this or that ſhall hurt thee. Now for the fourth thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>How wee may preſerue our peace. Anſ.</hi> Firſt, if euer wee knew it, this will help vs, to aſſure vs we haue it ſtil, To remember the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of peace with vs, is an eternall couenant; not for a day, but for euer. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 54 10, For, the mountaines ſhall moue, &amp;c. but my mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhal not depart from thee, neither ſhall my couenant of peace fall away, ſaith the Lord. I haue compaſſion on thee; the whole chapter to this purpoſe: and Chriſt ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the world cannot take away this peace from vs: if therefore it ſeem otherwiſe,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:17283:89"/> it is but hid in a cloud for a ſeaſon. Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> if we will keep this peace, we muſt not iudge according to ſenſe, but righteous iudgement, vvee muſt controule our ſenſe by ſanctified reaſon; which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth, that all things are for good to vs. When heer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low there are pitchy clouds, ſtormes, and ſuch like im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the air, the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry firmament hath no cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, the ſun hath the ſame bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes when it is hidden from vs, that it hath when it ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth moſt gloriouſly: ſo vvhen wee alter, and there is nothing but thunder, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſtorme in our sky, God is the ſame, the faithful mercies of the couenant are not changed. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vvee
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:17283:90"/> muſt, if our ſoules bee out a little, ſchoole them, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> doth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42. Why art thou caſt downe my ſoule? and why art thou ſo diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within me? There is an art of rocking the ſoule, and ſtilling it if out of quiet: the Lord teach it vs.</p>
            <p>Now for the doctrine: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> vve ſee how <hi>wee are to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then our ſelues with learning the doctrin of our peace through Christ: Paul</hi> was thus ſhod. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38.39, I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nothing ſhall ſeparate mee from the loue of God. All things, I knowe, worke together for the good of them that are beloued of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. And this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture made him goe ſuch hard vvaye cheerfully; in
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:17283:90"/> vvhich, ſhowrs of afflictions did fal as thick as hailſtones. The Church in the Canti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles 7.1. is commended, that her ſteps in theſe ſhooes are comely. This doth make Gods children, though not in the letter, yet in ſom ſort, tread vpon the Adder, Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisk, ſhake off Vipers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue no hurt; vvhereas if the feet be bared a little with the abſence of this (in ſenſe or faith) any thing ſmarteth ſore on vs. <hi>Iob</hi> 13.14, Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doo I take my fleſh in my teeth? And 6.3, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore novv my vvords are ſvvallovved vp. <hi>Ezechias,</hi> ſeeing God like a Lion, his peace ſomevvhat clouded, chattred like a Crane. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Where fore vvee beeing to gette our
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:17283:91"/> ſelues thus fenced againſt the craggednes of the vvay, how are they to bee blamed, that neuer labour to haue part in this peace vvhich the goſpel bringeth? They vvould be loth not to provide their bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies againſt vveather &amp; dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties of the vvay they go, but their ſoules they care not for. But look, as it is pitifull vvith one that goeth vpon ſharp flints, barefoot, &amp;c. or amongſt the thorns and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, ſo as the blood trickleth dovvne at euery ſtep: ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſhall thy naked ſoule bee, vvhen adverſitie ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if thou be not fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with this knovvledge of peace, through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, wee muſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee this our peace.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:17283:91"/> Oh that wee knewe theſe things concerning our peace! What could hurt? If the ſting be pulled forth of an Adder, vvee may play with it in our boſome: If vve know euery thing is for our good, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, wee may laugh when deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes. Aboue all things haue a care, that it be a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d peace; for there is in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and bodies, a double ſleepe; one ſicke, another ſound: now it is ſeene in the wakening. For ſick ſleep maketh vs when we awake ſo much the more ſicke, the other ſtrengtheneth vs: ſo peace is the ſoules ſleepe. Now if thy peace bee not ſound; when God ſhall wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thy conſcience, the
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:17283:92"/> more thou haſt ſlept, the more ſhall thy griefes be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, nay nothing ſhall ſting thee more then thy peace; woe to thee that art at peace: but if thou art at quiet, by knowing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of peace, by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, then it ſhall refreſh and ſtrengthen thee.</p>
            <p>Now followes the fourth thing, the ſhield of faith. Firſt, wee handle it general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in order as before. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, particularly from the circumſtances. Firſt, the manner of exhorting: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things. Secondly, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of it; that it can quench all the fierie darts, &amp;c. Firſt, the thing here meant is, a true liuely faith, laying holde on Chriſt
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:17283:92"/> for iuſtification; and in the reſt of Gods word and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll promiſes, for the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this preſent life: for not onely faith on Chriſt, but on the ſpeciall promiſes of God, is neceſſary for vs: not that theſe are two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kindes of faith, but one imployed diuerſly: as the ſoule in man working in the ſeuerall faculties of nature, is not three ſoules, but one, exerciſing three diuers fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Secondly, for the vſe of faith, it ſerveth not onely to iuſtifie vs, but to make vs endure in all affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, without making haſte. The iuſt liueth in time of his afflictions, by faith. Hee that beleeueth maketh not haſte. 2. It doth worke
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:17283:93"/> in vs, and guide the courſe of our obedience. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1 5. To the obedience of faith, not onely in beleeving the Goſpell, but the other word of command and promiſe. 3. It doth preuail againſt all enemies. This is the victory that ouercometh the world, euen our faith, 1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.4. The Vſe ſhall be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly branched out heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Thirdly, <hi>we must mark how the Diuell doth practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs in this point.</hi> 1. Hee will labour to put vpon vs, and ſerue vs with a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait faith. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> You beleeue that God is mercifull, and ſent his Sonne, to be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of mankinde: you meane well, and haue good hope to God-ward, that is
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:17283:93"/> enough; Hee that beleeueth ſhall be ſaued, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16. And all that can be ſaid for the Popiſh faith may bee brought hither. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> That faith that ſaueth vs, muſt worke by loue, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.6. It muſt purge our hearts, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9, And hee put no difference betweene vs and them, after that by faith he had purified their hearts. It muſt make vs to knowe, Chriſt hath giuen himſelfe for vs. <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.20, Thus I liue, yet not I now, but Chriſt liveth in mee: and in that I now liue, I liue by the faith in the ſonne of God, who hath loved me, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen himſelfe for mee. And bring Chriſt into our harts. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17, That Chriſt
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:17283:94"/> may dwell in your hearts by faith; that yee being rooted and grounded in loue, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, to haue a faith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good workes, a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge onely of a Saviour gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen to man-kinde: this will profit nothing. <hi>Iames</hi> 2.14, What availeth it my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, though a man ſay he hath faith, when he hath no workes? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> can the faith ſaue him, &amp;c. Secondly, <hi>He will labour to wreſt our faith from vs,</hi> more violently or crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the firſt, in this wiſe; <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus</hi> beleeved, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.11. <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp;c. Faith in temporiſers doth not availe them: that faith is no better, for they haue done many things, had ioy, kept the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles company, and gone
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:17283:94"/> as farre as thou. <hi>Anſw. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
                  </label> Wee muſt beare off this blowe, by learning to diſtinguiſh true faith from falſe faith, by foure things.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. For the nature of it; True faith doth apply Chriſt in particular, &amp; ſaith, with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Thomas,</hi> My Lord, and my God. Who hath loued mee, and giuen himſelfe for me. Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> it doth increaſe in the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the word and prayer, which did as Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, beget it. Now falſe preſumptions are careleſſe of theſe helpes. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It is perfected &amp; groweth vp, through temptations, wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtling with doubting feares. For if our faith bee a true fruit of the ſpirit; our luſt will fight againſt it, though
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:17283:95"/> we out-growe theſe things, in proceſſe of time. And therefore it is to be marked, that all other faiths, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell neuer ſifteth them: for either they are ſuch as vvill not perfect the parties; as luſts, temptations, &amp;c. or elſe ſuch as are his owne coyne, bearing his inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: as for example, carnal preſumption. And therfore hee letteth them paſſe for currant. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, a true faith is ſeene by this effect, It purgeth the heart, ſo that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doth not retaine the loue of any ſinne wherein it hateth to be reformed: the others come ſhort; as <hi>Herods</hi> did reach to many things, but not to leaue his <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rodias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Diuell will
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:17283:95"/> thus ſhake our faith; True faith is with many fruits, <hi>Iam.</hi> 2. Is accompanied with ioy. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8, Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wee reioyce, with ioy vnſpeakeable and glorious. Without doubting. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> doubted not, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20. neither did hee doubt of the promiſe, &amp;c. Now thou haſt no fruits, thou art without feeling, comfort, full of doubting. <hi>Anſ.</hi> We muſt examine, whether wee haue any fruits of faith vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, or none appearing: if wee haue few fruits, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a weak faith; not that there is no faith, dead trees haue not any fruit at all v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them. If we haue none, it muſt bee conſidered, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was ſo alwaies with
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:17283:96"/> vs, or by occaſion of ſome fall; hauing before beene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. Now, if in the firſt kinde, it is plaine, vve never had a true faith; if in the later, it argueth faith is in a ſwoone, or as a tree in the nipping froſt of winter. 2. For ſenſe of ioy wee muſt knowe, that it is a a fruit may be ſeuered from faith: as in Chriſt, vvhoſe beliefe vvas firme, yet all comfort eclipſed: as in that ſpeech, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me? <hi>And the reioycing of faith, is chiefly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed in three ſeaſons:</hi> Either in the firſt breeding of a Chriſtian, that the ioynts of him may bee knit, the ſtronger: or after great te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations out-wreſtled, that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:17283:96"/> the broken bones may bee comforted: or in times of perſecution &amp; martyrdome, that wee may bee heartened in it, to conſtant ſuffering. Witneſſe our reioycing in Chriſt Ieſus dayly. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> 4. The Diuell will ſay, true faith groweth from faith to faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. Grace is like a graine of muſtard ſeed. Now thy faith hath no growth, nay thou art now more doubting then thou haſt beene. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>True faith grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: it is true with theſe limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</hi> Firſt, that it is not felt in him alwaies, in whom it groweth. 2. It doth not growe in all times, it may decreaſe in ſome degree: the meaning thereof is, that the grace which is in the end,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:17283:97"/> ſhall be more then at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſhall haue his growth. Now, if the Diuell ſaith to any beleeuer, thy faith never had, nor ſhall haue any growth; The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may eaſily anſwer it, <hi>Faith hath two ſeaſons:</hi> One of peace and building it healthfully, the other of temptations. In the firſt it groweth, and often is diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by him, in whom it is. 2. It is in <hi>temptations.</hi> Now <hi>theſe are of two ſorts.</hi> Firſt, ſuch in which faith is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and maketh reſiſtance: as in outward croſſes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, feares, doubting of his pardon, gripes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Thirdly, lawes of evill, that play the Lord of miſ rule in our members.
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:17283:97"/> Now theſe (faith cauſing vs flie to prayer) ſeeke the word of promiſe, renew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: theſe, I ſay, faith doth thriue by: as there are ſome growing ſickneſſes, in which the body ſhooteth out, and when men haue beene awhile exerciſed they perceiue it: there are other temptations of ſpirituall ſlumber, whether the heart be halfe waking, or by ſome grieuous ſinne fallen into a dead ſleepe. In theſe, faith may bee diminiſhed: as the holy Ghoſt ſaith of their loue, they had loſt ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>5</label> 5. The Diuell will tell vs, where there it true faith, there the word is pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull and profitable. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13, The word is effectual in
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:17283:98"/> you that beleeue. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.3, The word did not profit where there is no faith to mingle it with. But thou ſeeſt not the words power, &amp; doſt not profit by it. <hi>Anſ. The inefficiency of the word is two-folde.</hi> Simple, when it hath no ſaving worke: or preparatiue; vvhen it is ſaid to worke nothing as it ſhould, as we deſire, as wee ſometime haue felt it.</p>
            <p>Now the firſt ſtandeth not with faith, the later doth: as for example, put Aquavitae into a dead mans mouth, and all the reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues that may be, they doe nothing vvith him: but giue food, or reſtoratiues to a man in a dropſie, or conſumption, though hee
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:17283:98"/> ſtill vvalke vveakely, and haue no appetite before, and hath flaſhing after, and qualms riding ouer the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, yet hee is preſerued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: now we ſay, things doe no good, when they do not ſo healthſomly nouriſh, as they vſe in ſound bodies. Now this later is the ſtate of a Chriſtian ſoule, not the former: hee may anſwere therefore by denying the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the reaſon; It is effectual, though it do work nothing vvith him, as he hath knowen it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>6</label> 6. The Diuell will thus ſuggeſt to thy conſcience: If e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thou didſt truly beleeue, God would heare thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but thou askeſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueſt not. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The forme
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:17283:99"/> of the reaſon is naught, as which runneth from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to receiuing. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt hearing, and ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that we are hard-by the effect. The firſt (in lawfull things asked, in the name of Ieſus, 16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 23.) is alwaies: the ſecond not-alwaies. For God when he heareth, often maketh as if he heard not, nay as if he were contrarily minded. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.44, Thou haſt couered thy ſelf as with a cloud, that our prayer ſhould not paſſe thorough, that is, thou ſeemeſt ſo in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. <hi>Dauid.</hi> How long wilt thou ſmoake againſt prayer, &amp;c. open thy eares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> 10. God made him ſee, hee heard him a good
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:17283:99"/> ſpace after: yet he did heare him from the firſt requeſt. This then is the ſtate of gods people. But God when hee heares doth make as though hee did not heare, yea vvere turned from them and their praiers in diſpleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>7</label> Seauenthly, true faith fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not: thine doth often faile, and thou art ſo weak, thou ſeeſt thou canſt not hould out. And the truth is, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> the beſt faith tried long, will limp a little. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.10.11, I ſaid in my feare, All men are liers, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1, And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid in his heart, I ſhall one day periſh by the hand of <hi>Saul,</hi> &amp;c. Is it not better for me that I ſaue my ſelfe in the land of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines, &amp;c? And vvee by
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:17283:100"/> experience finde, that often through vnbeleefe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiency, vve yeeld the buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kler, and leaue awhile claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that promiſe which onely can releeue vs. But the anſwer is, by learning what it is to haue true faith faile: <hi>there is a double failing;</hi> one of the grace, another of the worke: now this later, the worke, may ceaſe while faith doth not faile: as <hi>Luke</hi> 22.32, But I haue praied for thee, that thy faith faile not. Yet compared with the end, <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion, vvhich was the worke of faith, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his mouth, and yet the grace was ſafe in his heart: for Chriſt was heard in that hee praied for. So that if the reaſon he thus framed, That
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:17283:100"/> faith which faileth in the worke is a falſe faith, this is a falſe ſentence. If hee ſay to mee, Thine faileth in the grace, it is falſly ſpoken to a true beleeuer, to make his grace extinct when the work faileth: for vve might aſwell ſay a man is dead when hee ſleepeth. And for his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that it ſhall faile, vvee muſt remember, that hell gates ſhall not preuaile. Hee hath praied, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>8</label> Eightly, the diuell he will from ſenſe and reaſon vvea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our beleefe: Thus hee kept <hi>Sarah</hi> in vnbeleef. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.12, She laughed, becauſe the thing ſpoken was againſt reaſon. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> For anſwer vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, vvee muſt knovve, They are bleſſed that beleeue and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:17283:101"/> ſee not, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.29. that vve vvalk by faith, not by ſight. Againe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1, Faith is the euidence of things not ſeene: vvee muſt therefore ſhake hands vvith this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving ſenſe and reaſon, if vvee vvill make vvay to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the divel vvill mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter many troubles againſt vs, and thus labour to ſhake our faith. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31, Hee vvinnovved <hi>Peters</hi> faith, by bringing him into ieopardy of his life. So vvhen many beleeue, he ſtirs the tongues of naughty ones to vvhippe them; if God giue leaue, he croſſeth them in their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and othervviſe: not that he plaieth ſo ſmal games as to blot their name, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:17283:101"/> for their money; but he ſhooteth at this, to vnſettle them in the vvay of faith, which they haue entred. But <hi>we muſt reſiſt thus,</hi> by getting knowledge, that Chriſt vvill not let our ſmoking vveek be put out; that theſe things ſhall vvorke to our good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. I but vve feele the contrarie, they vvorke ſo vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. <hi>Anſ.</hi> He that beateth a torch, ſeemeth to put out the light for a ſeaſon, yet it maketh it burne more cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: the ſhaking of trees ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them root deeper. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by learning the means of holding our faith: vvhich follovv. Theſe are his more violent practiſes; vvre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of our faith from vs: novv <hi>his more ſubtill ſleights
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:17283:102"/> are, his making vs to preſume on outward helps, &amp; withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our hearts by them.</hi> Thus, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.7. he did preuail againſt <hi>Aſa:</hi> for vvhen hee ſeeth vs hould the rocke where vve are ſafe from him, hee vvill ſet before vs other things, ſutable to our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt natures; knovving, that ſo much as vve come to leane on theſe, ſo much vve come to leaue our GOD. Thus hee houldeth out our Lady, Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> in the Romiſh Church; and by the creature, vvithdravv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the hearts of the people from their Creator. In which and other like practices, the divell is like a Fovvler that hath calls ſo like the natural notes, that birds come vnto
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:17283:102"/> them: ſo theſe ſpeake our mother tongue, and haue a note ſo liking to the reaſon and ſenſe of vs, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare it, but wee are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to flee vnto it. But <hi>wee muſt preuent this miſchiefe by christian caution:</hi> the diuells exchange will proue robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, wee ſhall change a rocke for a ſplitted reed, which wil hurt vs in the end. Hee that leaveth his God, forſaketh his mercy. <hi>Ionah</hi> 2.8, They that wait vpon lying vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, forſake their owne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. Againe, <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.5, Curſed is hee that maketh fleſh his arme, truſting in any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thing. Secondly, vve muſt know, that theſe things cannot do ought for vs, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Lord of Hoſts
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:17283:103"/> ſhall command them: he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them at pleaſure. The horſe and chariot is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but victory is from the God of battell: many ſeeke the face of the Iudge, but iudgement is from the Lord: men riſe vp early, but GOD builds the city: we may vſe meat and medicine, but God is our life, and length of our daies: and it is ſeen, the ſwift hath not the race, the vviſe wanteth bread.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>the diuell will labour to ſupplant our faith by indirect wayes leading to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe,</hi> and ſeeming to put an end to our euils: for, ſeeing that vvee are weary in endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and would fain ſee reſt from troubles, he then will open poſtern doors, indirect
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:17283:103"/> vvaies of deliuerance; like Fowlers, when all is hard froſt and ſnovve, they ſhew meat, that birds ſharply ſet, may flee on murder. Thus <hi>Sarah, Gen.</hi> 16.2, And <hi>Sarah</hi> ſayd, Behold novv the Lord hath reſtrained mee from childe-bearing, I pray thee go-in vnto my maid, it may be that I ſhall receiue a child by her. <hi>Dauid,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 27.1, Is it not better for me that I ſaue my ſelfe in the land of the Philiſtines, &amp;c? Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4, Command theſe ſtones to bee made bread by miracle, novv thou art hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry. We muſt therefore take heed, that vvee often thinke on that in <hi>Eſay,</hi> Hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth, maketh not haſte: and conſider againe, that the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:17283:104"/> eaſe of ſuch meanes, is like to a draught of drinke to a hot ague, it maketh the fire burne worſe after: your iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue in this kinde, is but brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the iaile which maketh vs ſubiect to double puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now followeth the fourth conſideration, how we may keep our faith againſt all aſſaults, &amp; encreaſe it.</hi> Firſt, by expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſelf-confidence, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe: Secondly, by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations that lead directly to the ſtrengthening of our faith: Thirdly, rules of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Firſt, <hi>he that will beleeue, muſt deny all truſt in his owne wiſdome: for, ſelfe-confidence is a choak-weed of beleefe. Pro.</hi> 3.5, Truſt in the Lord with all thy heart, and leane not
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:17283:104"/> to thy owne wiſedome. We are the circumciſion, vvho haue no confidence in the fleſh, but reioyce in Chriſt Ieſus. And as we can growe downe, denying our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and all ſtrength wee can make: ſo ſhall faith on our great God growe vp. 2. Wee muſt ſtrike at vnbeleef, with the ſword of the ſpirit, taking vp our ſelues for hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, with ſuch like places as theſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, Now the iuſt ſhall liue by faith: but if any vvithdrawe himſelfe, my ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him. As the murmuring and vnbeleeuing Iſraelites, who would not beleeue the Lords oath giuen them, that he vvould make them dwell in the temporall Land <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:17283:105"/> were accordingly ſhut out of it: ſo faithleſſe ones, who beleeue not Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, concerning the true Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kingdome, ſhall be barred from entring that holy place. See <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.29.30.31.32. Chewing on ſuch words, will tame the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of vnbeliefe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the iniurious effects vvhich this ſinne doth to God, and vs. For vnbeliefe giveth God the lie. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.10. Hee that beleeveth not in God, maketh him a lyer: then which, what can bee more reproachfull? and it doth vs all the harme: for nothing could hurt vs, if this were not. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 <hi>vlt.</hi>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:17283:105"/> They could not enter for vnbeleefe, they were a chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh lewd people, beſides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtempers: but this did them the miſchiefe, for it reiecteth the medicines, that would cure vs, taken; and pulleth off Gods plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which lying on would ſalue our miſeries,: thus purging out this malignant humour, we ſhall ſtrengthen faith the more commodi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſly. Firſt, by looking vp to Chriſt, when vve feel our faith weake, calling him the beginner, the finiſher of faith in vs: praying him to encreaſe our faith, and to helpe our vnbeliefe; thou muſt giue it, and worke it in me, or I cannot haue it. A fainting bodie will taſte
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:17283:106"/> ſomething that is cordiall, and reſtoratiue: and a fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoule muſt baite it ſelfe, with looking to Ieſus, who is our cordiall, and reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, and every thing. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wee muſt conſider whom we truſt, for this will ſtrenghten beleefe: it is not with God as with man, who is better knowen often, then truſted. The mother of our vnbeleefe is, the ignorance of the affectionate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. Thoſe that knowe thee, will truſt in thee: this confirmed <hi>Paul</hi> in faith, becauſe hee knew him, hee truſted to. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12, For I know who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue beleeued, &amp;c. and I knowe that hee is able to keepe that I haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:17283:106"/> vnto him, vntill that day. Now concerning God, two things muſt be known. Firſt, his power. Secondly, his truth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.21, Being fully aſſured, that hee which had promiſed, was able alſo to doe it. <hi>Abraham</hi> was thus ſtrengthened. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.11. <hi>Sarah</hi> beleeved, for hee was faithfull that had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed: and for example, I by faith beleeue my ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all liberty in Chriſt, ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, my life, ioy, &amp;c. How ſhould I ſupport my ſelfe, when I ſee nothing but thraldome, and ſinne raigning in mee, nothing in me but deadneſſe of heart? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thus: hee that hath ſpoken this to mee, Holde me, I will ſet thee free, I wil
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:17283:107"/> circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſe thy heart, waſh it, purge it, heale it of all rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions: hee that hath ſpoken it, is God Almighty, that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth Beeing to all creatures wee ſee, and that inuiſible world of ſpirits; that calleth the things that are not, as if they were: that if there were no print of theſe things in mee, can increaſe them gloriouſly: and as hee is able, ſo he is true &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to keep touch, his word being purer then ſiluer ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times refyned. Thirdly, wee muſt labour to ſee the preciouſneſſe of our faith: and this ſeene, vvill make vs holde hard, ere vvee part with it. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3, To you vvhich haue obtained like precious faith with vs. A
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:17283:107"/> man that hath great charge, his whole ſtate about him, will as ſoone loſe his life as part with his treaſure. Now, in marking what it dooth, vvee ſhall ſee how precious it is. For what a grace is that, which when vve are buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vvith Satan, doth make vs to ſtand? when our wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons are beaten on our heads, our prayers leſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, when vve are laid along, doth raiſe vs? vvhen ouer charged with afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, doth ſtill lift our head to Chriſt our Lord? and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs ſay, hee is ours, wee a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his, fire and water muſt not diuorce vs. And <hi>this for the generall handling of the verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="208" facs="tcp:17283:108"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Now for the particular.</hi> Firſt, from the manner. 1. Aboue all. 2. The fruite or vſe of faith: with which you may be able to quench all the fiery darts of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. Firſt, then wee heare, <hi>that aboue all things wee muſt labour after faith, our care muſt bee chiefly about this.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.23, This then is his commandement, that wee beleeue in the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. This is Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with wee are charged. For nothing is ſo glorious to God. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.33, It doth giue God a teſtimoniall, as it were, of his truth, and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth that he is true: and for our ſelues, the holy Ghoſt maketh all our riches to
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:17283:108"/> come in of it. <hi>Iam.</hi> 2.5, The poore God hath choſen to bee rich in faith; not onely that faith it ſelfe is a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pearle, but becauſe that by faith vvee haue all thoſe vnſearchable riches of Chr. our Lord: and the manner of our deliuerie doth ſhew vs plainely, what care wee muſt haue of it. For if wee bidde a ſeruant buy many things, but aboue all ſuch a thing; hee would gather vvhat hee ſhould bee moſt carefull in: So heere get o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, but aboue all, faith. Thus <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 2.20, Thus now I liue by the faith, &amp;c. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 11, All thoſe Saints pleaſing God, had this beleefe towardes him. <hi>Now then to the dooing
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:17283:109"/> of this, wee muſt labour to fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret out our vnbeleefe.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>to enkindle and renew our dying faith, &amp; encreaſe it: the first wee ſhall finde theſe waies.</hi> Firſt, marke how vve are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted to the worde of threatning; vvhether it breed in vs feare, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full declining of ſinne. If we ye liue after the fleſh ye ſhal d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. If this were beeleeved, vve durſt as well take a Bear by the tooth, as give the raines to our corruptions. Who is ſo hardy as to thruſt his finger into the fire? but vve often though vve know nothing, let our ſelues bee carried vvith luſts through vnbelief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Secondly, let vs marke how vve are aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted to the promiſe. We ſee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:17283:109"/> by a civill faith vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue man, therefore, if vvee haue a mans word, for this that vvas deſperate, vvee are glad, wee ſeeke to get ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. If vve haue bonds we box them vp; we knowe, vvhen they expire, vvhat to chalenge by vertue of them. Now for the promiſe of God, which ſecureth vs of all good temporall, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, who enquireth after it, who ſeeketh it in his hart, vvho reioyceth in it, vvho ſaith, I look for ſuch a thing, by vertue of ſuch a word, my God hath ſpoken? which argueth wee are full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe. Thirdly, <hi>our reſting in mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and leaning to them.</hi> For, ſo much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he heart doth reſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="212" facs="tcp:17283:110"/> is by ſin withdrawen from the Creator. <hi>But how may wee finde this? By marking how it is with vs three waies.</hi> Firſt, if wee vſed meanes, as not vſing them, what means ſoever we had, our fear and truſt to God would bee the ſame as if we vvanted them: For vve would knowe, that further then God did ſend forth his vvord, they could doe nothing. Secondly, if vvee did our duties, and meanes were vvanting, vvee vvould bee confident; ſtill remembring that of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan,</hi> It is all one with God, to ſaue with many, or vvith few; with ſmall means, as great. Thirdly, when we haue things vvee vvould thinke little of any meanes;
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:17283:110"/> but aſcribe all to Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Now vve do the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to theſe: For if vvee haue meanes, vpon them we are ſecure; as a man is frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, hee hopes to haue his cauſe ended, though iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to come from the Lord: if the Iudge him ſelfe were made for vs, and if all meanes be at hand, vvee can reſt; vvee are ſo fledge that till ſomething croſſe vs, the Lord is not cloven to, and ſought to by vs. Againe, if this or that (requiſite in our Iudgements) cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; though we vvere ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo diligent, wee diſtruſt, and ſuſpect the ſucceſſe, ſaying, that it cannot proue vvell. And againe, in the third place, when vvee haue
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:17283:111"/> things, our affections doe more liuely vvorke on this or that, vvhich fell out (as men ſpeake) more luckily, then on Gods bleſſing, which is all in all. Which ſheweth our ſecret reſting in the creature. Fourthly, our tottering vvhen vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; If we did vvalk, truſting on God, vve ſhould be like mount <hi>Sion,</hi> foure ſquare; men, howſoeuer throwen downe, ſtanding firmely, vvheras the leaſt thing doth vnſettle vs. Shall God offer to paſſe his vvord, yea giue his Indenture to me, for all good things, ſhal I not look after it? the points of our hearts ſtill turned to the povver, goodneſſe, faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our God, which was
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:17283:111"/> and is the matter of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence? If weather faile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhile, men are, as if God vvould quite forget them: if doings doe decay, ſuch a vvorld for taking they haue not known the like: if croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ouertake vs, wee are at our wits ends. He that hath crutches, if hee learne not on them walking, take away his crutches, hee walketh ſtill: but take away a crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples crutches, that goeth on them, and hee commeth to the ground preſently. So if wee did not like to crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on theſe things, vve ſhould not be ſo eaſily throwen dovvne in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueall: ſo the impatient breaking off in holding the promiſe, the double dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:17283:112"/> and exceſſiue care. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.3, Shall hee not do much more for you, O yee of little faith? The ſhifts and ſinfull courſes vvhich men admit to thriue by, all proue, that there is not right faith in vs tovvards God.</p>
            <p>Now the cure of this is, by being diſpleaſed with our ſelues, taking vp our ſoules in this manner; If the King or a great man ſhould threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mee, would I not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, and carefull to decline their wrath? Shall my God threaten me, and I be ſecure and careleſs? If I haue a mans word or bond that is of worth I write vpon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as if I had it: Shall I not ioyfully reſt in the word, ſeale and oath of my God?
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:17283:112"/> If a man of worth ſhould be asked a pawne, and not cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited on his word, he would take it in euill part: What a ſhame is it, that I will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue GOD, further then I haue his caution? If I would not truſt a man for a few pence, would I truſt him for pounds? Cannot I truſt God for the things of this life, and do I ſay truely, that I truſt him for life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting? With ſuch reaſoning, a man muſt make that ſinne lothſome to his ſoule; and then ſeeing himſelfe a maſſe of vnbeleefe, muſt look vnto Chriſt, and call to him, as the authour and finiſher of faith, muſt cry Lord helpe my vnbeleefe, muſt ſet the promiſes before him, and
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:17283:113"/> chaine himſelfe faſt to the meditation of them. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Seeing then we ſhould giue ſuch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence this way, how are they then to be blamed, that ſeeke not after it, lying in vnbeleefe? How are others to bee taxed, who, though they haue faith, never awake themſelues to lay hould of God? Which the Prophet bewaileth, <hi>Eſay</hi> 64 7, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> There is none that ſtirreth vp h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp;c. And it doth teach vs our duty, euen to liue the life of faith in al things, euen in regard of naturall actions and ciuil, to ſee Chriſt moue vs in them. In feeding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to hold Chr. by faith, that his ſpirit may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ach vs to eat &amp; drink to his glory, that is, with fear, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:17283:113"/> ſobriety<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> remembring of our duty, which wee are after to performe. If wee goe hither or thither, vvee muſt doo it by faith, ſeeing vvee mooue in God, and he is the keeper of our out-goings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commings. If vvee ſleep, we muſt not onely conſider f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding which cauſe; but the promiſe of God that giueth ſleepe to his beloued: yea, vvee muſt apprehend God as our life, and length of our daies, not reſting in temperan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond thing to bee mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, is, the commendations of faith, teaching vs, what fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rce is in faith to keep vs against all aſſaults of the diuell.</hi> Wee are kept by the power of GOD through faith to ſalvation,
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:17283:114"/> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. This one is as all the reſt, and therefore is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our victory, which ouer commeth the world, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4. And it is ſo mighty, that the powers of hell cannot preuaile againſt it. <hi>Now for the fuller vnderſtanding, you muſt knowe what is meant by fiery darts; ſecondly, how faith doth extinguiſh them.</hi> It is a borrovved ſpeech from poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned darts, vvhich venime and cauſe fiery heat in the perſon they enter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo all thoſe courſes vvhereby Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſendeth ſcorching heat into the ſoule, are noted by them: theſe are either terrors apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding a wrath which is a fire that drinketh the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh. And <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.5, Fightings vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:17283:114"/> terrors vvithin, vve had no reſt; or ſinful luſts vvhich hee doth vvreath againſt vs, vvhich are as fire. <hi>Iames</hi> 3, fire of hell. <hi>Iob</hi> 31, Adultery a fire burning to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; or outvvard calamities and perſecutions, vvhich are called heats and fiery trials. Novv faith doth quench theſe after a double manner, ſometime not letting them enter, but doth latch them, that they do fall off vvithout pearcing vs. This <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7, vvhen the lavv came, ſavv his curſednes. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. had invvard terrours, the diuell likewiſe did buffet him with ſinfull ſuggeſtions, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. Hee had troubles as thick as hailſtones, following him, yet this preuail'd not againſt
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:17283:115"/> him, becauſe hee kept the faith. <hi>Peter, Luke</hi> 22, had the dart ſtuck in him awhile: but faith did renew repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and healed him, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the poiſon of ſin a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.34, By faith the Saints endured all affliction, yea quenched the fire, yea choſe them before releaſe. And wee ſee by experience, that when the diuell doth lighten about vs with the wilde fire of luſts, tempting vs to them, that when vvee looke to Chriſt, as who hath diſſolued the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, who hath crucified the power of them, &amp; ſaid, they ſhall not raigne ouer vs; this doth ſlake the fire. Againe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fears aſſault vs, coming to peace in Chriſt, vvee are
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:17283:115"/> ſaued: when troubles come, faith maketh vs liue like the buſh in the fire, without bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>Whrefore this muſt <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 1. teach vs how wretched their eſtate is, who beleeue not, vvho haue not their mindes and hearts ſo vvrought towards Chriſt, that his ſpirit hath made them nevv creatures: they that haue not this faith, ly open to all the aſſaults of the diuell. He that beleeueth not, Gods vvrath is on him, the fiery darts ſticke in him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it muſt teach vs to ſeek after this: for God thus highly praiſeth it, that knovving the vvorth of it, vvee may labour after it. If enemies did beſiege vs, were it not vvell vvith him that
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:17283:116"/> vvere locked vp in a tovver invincible? ſo vvhen death and enmity cometh againſt vs, this faith doth lock vs in Gods faithfulneſſe, mercie and povver, that nothing can hurt vs.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> That faith hath this effect, is a notable diſſvvaſiue from euer embracing this popiſh faith, the vvhich is ſeuered from all affiance, and vvhich a man may haue (by their ovvne confeſſion) and bee vvounded vvith deſpair, and bee full of all deadly ſinne: their faith therfore is a vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhield; it is ſo far from defending vs from all the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry darts of the diuell, that a man may haue it, and bee an incarnate diuell.</p>
            <p>Novv follovveth hope:
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:17283:116"/> for ſaluation is here put for hope of it; the thing hoped for, for the hope it ſelfe. For thus it is conſtrued, 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.8. Firſt, therefore it may bee asked, What hope this is? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Not only hope of ſaluation, which ſhall bee in the laſt day, but of all te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deliuerance from euill. And it may bee deſcribed, A certaine expecting to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine every thing faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth, grounded onely on Gods grace.</p>
            <p>The proper work of hope is, to make vs expect: which is to be marked. For, meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the word by our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acception, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing it from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectance in heauen; it is one ground (amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers)
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:17283:117"/> of the Papiſts errours, whereas expectation in the life to come differeth not from hope, in that it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine expectation (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.20, I certainely look for &amp; hope) but in this; Firſt, that our expectation heere is grounded in faith, that in ſight; this acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pani'd with grief, that without any difficulty. Secondly, it is a certaine expecting not in it ſelfe, but neuer fayling the party which hopeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which muſt be vnderſtood not as if it were certaine in his ſenſe, but in the eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: the reaſon is becauſe hope han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth on faith, which in that it beleeueth is certaine: if the pin be ſure, that which hangeth on it cannot fall.
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:17283:117"/> Thirdly, the obiect is not ſtrictly eternall life, but all the good things temporall and eternall, which faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth. Laſtly, the means on which hope leaneth, is here ſet downe, Gods grace. Truſt perfectly (the vvord is hope) on the grace of God in Chriſt, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. Not parting ſtakes, halfe on grace, halfe on workes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, hope expecteth ſo to obtaine as faith beleeueth; but faith beleeueth through the word of promiſe, not through working, <hi>Gal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.3. A perſon ſo ſoone as hee is a t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue conuert, hath hope as well as loue, though hee hath no workes as yet: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can a houſe be built and a foundation bee layd after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard.
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:17283:118"/> Beſides, if he ſhould die on his conuerſion, and being receiued though hee had done no good workes, hee ſhould bee ſaued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to hope. And this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror hath three things which occaſion it. They conceiue that workes are partiall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of our ſaluation, with mercy; becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures vſe ſuch conditionall ſpeeches, If you mortfie the deedes of the fleſh, yee ſhall liue, &amp;c. But theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are ſpoken to parties al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready now beleeuing, &amp; are conditions that follow, not cauſes going before an heire of ſaluation. If vvee ſay to our children, Be good chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ply your bookes, you ſhall be my heire; who wold
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:17283:118"/> gather, that going to ſchool is the cauſe of inheritance. Secondly, they diſtinguiſh not betwixt that which hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth hope, and that vvhich erecteth it to hope, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that on vvhich it dependeth in hoping: but theſe are farre different. If the ſtomack be vvell, that neither fumes nor diſtillations trouble, the eye ſeeth cleerly: yet the eye doth not depend on the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, as the means of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſo if the conſcience be not ſurcharged (fume not vp accuſations, feares, &amp;c.) the eye of the ſoule ſeeth cleerely: vvhich vvee may tearme hope; Yet it doth not depend on the goodnes of the conſcience, as the cauſe why it hopeth. And
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:17283:119"/> hence it is, that they abuſe Scripture, vvhich ſhew the cheery hoping of a good conſcience, as if they proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that our hope expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as well by vvorkes as mercy to attaine that wee look for. Thirdly, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not, that theſe are ſuch Theologicall vertues, as are appropriated to God, and are no way communicable with the creature. Why you vvill ſay, loue is ſo too, yet wee may loue the creature: t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ankfulneſſe, yet wee may thank the creature. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It may be ſayd we loue not ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolutely, but in &amp; for God, and after a ſort loue God in the creature, as hee loving vs (ſo farre as his work) lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe in vs, but the
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:17283:119"/> reaſon is not alike of theſe: For, therefore wee loue the creature, and giue thankes, becauſe there is in them matters of loue, and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving; but there is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ground hope on, in the creature. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 108, Giue vs helpe againſt trouble, for vaine is the helpe of man. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127, It is in vaine to riſe early, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.3, There is no help in Princes. Why, may one ſay; Hath not God put vertue in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to doe thus, and thus; as in a horſe to carry one, in a medicine to heale one? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hee hath, but yet the exerciſe of this power, hee keepeth in dependance on himſelfe; and cannot be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then hee pleaſeth to
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:17283:120"/> put it forth. For till he who is the Lord of Hoaſtes bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſend foorth his word, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107, and giue them their moouing, they can do nothing. As, I haue power to goe to ſuch a place: yet God maketh me in it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on his pleaſure. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4, I will doe this, &amp;c. if God will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the vſe of this helmet is, firſt, to ſtrengthen faith;</hi> which is the principal, &amp; firſt thing in the new creature, as the helmet couereth the head of the bodie: but faith, you vvill ſay, breedeth hope; yet hope is ſuch a daughter, as is a ſtaffe to her aged mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Secondly, it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the battery of our daily diſtreſtes, and impreſſions
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:17283:120"/> of deſpaire. I had fainted, had I not looked to ſee the goodnes of the Lord in the Land of the living. For hope that God will ſend ſtrength, and giue iſſue, doe ſo holde vp the chinne that we ſinke not in deep waters. <hi>For the third thing, the Diuell doth ſeeke many waies to disfurniſh vs of this munition.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> Firſt, by putting vs off with hope that will not ſerue, falſe, vaine hopes, wicked hopes; ſuch as are the preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptions of many, who by their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt liues, who with ſaying Lord have mercy on vs, though they lie in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the luſt of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; yet ſay, they haue good hopes. Theſe are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked hopes, and to hope vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:17283:121"/> vaine grounds: as on this, that God hath bleſſed vs, with outward things; that therefore wee are in his fauour: but all our hope muſt bee brought to this touch ſtone, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3, Hee that hath this hope purgeth himſelfe, even as he is pure. Hee that hath true hope to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, will bee carefull to cleanſe out all corruption of fleſh and ſpirit, which are diſpleaſing to God. If wee hope to haue any good from man, we vvill be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full not to incurre his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, doe that which he deſireth. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Whoſoeuer nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth hopes from God, wil not liue in ſinne which God hateth. Secondly, if wee haue hope, the Divell will
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:17283:121"/> labour many waies to break it off, by pleading againſt vs our vnworthineſſe. If thy conſciende did not tel thee, thou art thus, then mighteſt thou haue hope, and that by cutting the cable which will make vs looſe our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>There is double vnworthineſſe;</hi> one of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill conſcience that lieth in ſome ſinne, of which it will not bee reformed: another vnworthineſſe of a good conſcience, which deſireth and endeauoureth to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burthened of ſinne, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; and therefore daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth repentance. Now this vnworthineſs doth not take away hope: for God doth make good his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not for our ſakes, the
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:17283:122"/> houſe of Iſraell, but for his Names ſake. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.32, Bee it knowen vnto you, I doe it not for your ſake; the zeale of the Lord of Hoſtes which hee beareth vs doth it: he leapeth over the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of <hi>Bether,</hi> to come to vs; or if hee ſtayed on our ſufficient diſpoſitions, wee might all bid our hope fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, From delay the Diuell will ſhake hope. <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.20, Hope delayed maketh a ſicke ſoule. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> But we muſt knowe, that Gods for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance is no quittance. And when theſe vſurers care not how much their money runs in a rich mans hands; why ſhould we think much to truſt our treaſure with
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:17283:122"/> God? who will pay vſe for time hee delayeth. Againe, he doth not foreſlack any fit ſeaſon, but onely waiteth the opportunity: and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of delayed hopes, yet certainely accompliſhed at length, may comfort vs. Seauenty yeares, the retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Gods people from the Babyloniſh captiuity was reiourned, yet it was fulfilled in the ſeaſon of it. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, from the greatneſſe of our miſerie. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.18, And I ſayd, my ſtrength, &amp; my hope is periſhed from the Lord; reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring mine affliction, my worm-wood, and my gall. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Not to bee mooued at preſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, wee muſt firſt learn wiſedome, not to revolue
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:17283:123"/> them ſo much, as to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied by them. He that will drinke a potion, will not roule euery drop about his mouth; and hee that will goe thorough afflictions, muſt not demurre too deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon them. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> looked not at things ſeene, but vnſeene. The end of the croſſe muſt bee eyed, or the croſſe will not bee endured. Yet wee muſt not, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, run vpon fooliſh light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that will not let the heart goe into any mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: this is as dangerous a worke, as deſpaire it ſelfe. 2. We muſt remember that hope ſhewes it ſelfe, when things are hopeleſſe. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> hoped againſt hope. <hi>Iob</hi> 13.13, If hee kill mee, yet
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:17283:123"/> vvill I truſt in him. Thirdly, vvhen things preſſe vs moſt, vvee are neereſt our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: <hi>Quum duplicantur la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teres, venit Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, hopes haue miſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>6</label> and therefore are not to be truſted to. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.25. And theſe all through faith obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a good report, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not the promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. To the firſt, firſt we may thus anſwer: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> reiecting the Papiſts opinion, that it was humane credulity, not chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hope, we may ſay, that in ſome ſort it was fulfilled, though he neuer was freed: for, God did in his firſt audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence giue him deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Nero</hi> for a ſeaſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee might haue beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the Philippians.</p>
            <pb n="240" facs="tcp:17283:124"/>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>hope is twofould:</hi> of things heauenly, or things earthly; now the later may miſſe of vs, and yet hope re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth certaine, becauſe hope ſo looketh for them, as faith laieth hold of them: now faith doth not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them abſolutely, but ſo far forth as they ſhall bee good for vs. For, that place in the <hi>Hebrews</hi> proueth, that all things beleeued and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for, are not preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vpon death. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not therefore, that they are fruſtrate: we dying ſhall not preſently haue the things promiſed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the reſurrection of the body, yet our faith &amp; hope cannot miſ-carry in it. <hi>Now fourthly the meanes, whereby
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:17283:124"/> wee may ſtrengthen our hope.</hi> Firſt, to conſider the nature of it, and the promiſe annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it; It maketh not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, it ſhall bee reioycing. <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.18, The hope of the righteous ſhall bee gladnes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the work of it for the preſent: it doth refreſh vs, and renew our ſtrength. <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. <hi>vlt.</hi> But they that wait on the Lord, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their ſtrength, they ſhall lift vp their wings as the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, they ſhall run and not bee weary, they ſhall walke and not faint: if this ſpirit of hope bee in vs, vvee like a blowen bladder ſinke not in our diſtreſſes; if this bee downe, wee hang the wing: and daily vſe of it ſhould make vs ſtudiouſly maintain
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:17283:125"/> and increaſe it. Thirdly, to thinke how we do in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things: vvee will wait vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things vncertaine, dead mens ſhooes, attend perſons early &amp; late for a good iſſue in ſome ſuit, buy reuerſions, and reſpect them, though neuer like to fal in our time. Who is great like our God? Shall wee not attend his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? What is precious like grace? Shall wee not vvait on it? Thus <hi>Iames,</hi> 5.7, from that the husbandman doth in earthly things, doth teach vs our duty of patient expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting things heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, it will confirme vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member experiences fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed, the preſidents of good hope, how God hath made thoſe partakers of
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:17283:125"/> their hopes, whom hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue put out of his ſight; <hi>Dauid:</hi> his people in Babylon, &amp;c. So to thinke how ſweet they ſhall bee to vs when they come. Hope vvhen it cometh is a tree of life, <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.12.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Now then the doctrine of this is, that <hi>Christians, by the grace of hope, muſt ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then themſelues in their conflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting daies.</hi> If wee want good things ſpirituall, wee muſt walk by hope; looking to him, who hath ſaid, we ſhall want nothing that is good. If in aduerſity, we muſt hope to haue a good iſſue out of it, our liues muſt bee paſſed in looking for our full deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance which ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in the laſt time. Thus,
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:17283:126"/> 
               <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123, our eies are to thee as the eies of a hand-maid to her miſtreſſe, till thou ſhevv mercy on vs. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> was a iuſt man, looking for the conſolation of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> in his croſſes had this hope. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20, But our conuerſation is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whence wee looke for the Sauiour, &amp;c. he conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, looking for his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glory. This is our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor: without it our liues would bee toſſed with the billowes and ſurges of our manifould temptations; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially vve muſt remember to vvaigh this anchor in a ſafe road: for the Papiſts caſt it on the ſands, euen on their ovvne vvorthineſſe, vvhich maketh their head peece as
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:17283:126"/> ſtrong as a helmet of brown paper. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> But (alas) vvee are naked chriſtians: vvhen vve are in trouble, vvee are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to vviſh our ſelues dead, hopeleſſe voices paſſe from vs, vvee neuer look to ſee it othervviſe, and our corne (as vvee ſay) is ſhaken vvith euery vvinde for vvant of this ſupporter. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Wee muſt be exhorted on the contrary to wait on God: if in troubles, for the iſſue; if in want, for ſupply; if he be abſent, when hee ſhall returne. This hope is a Dormant with vs, we do not looke vp the practice of it: if wee ſend a Letter, vvee looke till wee receiue an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: vvee can ſay, I ſhould heare from ſuch a place, &amp;c. Who looketh till God retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:17283:127"/> an anſwer of his mind which he hath often ſent to him by praier? If one ſaith, I will bee vvith you to help you, or doo this or that for you, vvee looke hee ſhould keepe touch accordingly: if one ſend vs vvord hee vvill bee vvith vs, vvee looke and prepare till he commeth: but if GOD ſpeake, who doth vvait? though he forewarne vs of his coming, vvho doth attend? Wee vvould be loth to tell an vntruth, &amp;c. but theſe great things, of negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting faith and hope, vvee make no conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of: when Mint and Cummin muſt bee giuen, the great things of the lavv muſt not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
            <p>Novv follovvs the ſvvord
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:17283:127"/> of the ſpirit; ſo cald becauſe it is put in our hands, and made mighty through the vvorke of this ſpirit. Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>that which is heere vnderstood by the word of God, is, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer out of the written word we haue by reading and hearing, or what God doth teach vs by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, agreeable with that which is in the word written.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>for the vſe,</hi> it is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther defenſiue, vvarding the blovves vvhich Satan doth reach vs (as Chriſt vſed, <hi>Mat</hi> 4.) or offenſiue, it doth ſtrike dovvn the darknes &amp; povv<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er of ſinne vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>the diuell doth keep men from this ſword by excuſes,</hi> they are not book-learned, haue not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as others, to looke into ſuch matters, vvhy may not
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:17283:128"/> men bee ſaued vvithout knovving the vvord? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Search the Scriptures: for in them yee think to haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.39. Againe, firſt ſeek Gods kingdome, &amp; the righteouſnes thereof, &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. No ſeed ſovven, there can be no harveſt; no vvord, vvhich is the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall ſeed, there can be no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting to God. If vve haue the vvord vvith vs, firſt <hi>hee will impugne it by ſuggeſtions,</hi> thus;<note place="margin">Ob.</note> Hovv canſt thou tell this is the vvord of God: it is not his vvord. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> We muſt remooue theſe things vvhich are ſparkes of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme in vs; Firſt, by taking to heart the groſſe Atheiſme and vnbeleefe of our hearts, and ſeeking to be purged of
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:17283:128"/> it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by crying for the eye ſalue of the ſpirit of illumination. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by obeying that wee knowe, which doth open the door of the heart wide, for the holy Ghoſt to enter, which doth aſcertain euery thing. Secondly, from want of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in vs. Hee wil make light of it. <hi>Obiect.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Men ſay, Men ſay, this is ſo effectuall, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable: but what ſweetnes, what power, what terrour doeſt thou finde, in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes or threatnings of it? And who are worſe then they that liue vnder it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> We muſt diſtinguiſh, from that the word doth of it owne nature, and that which the corruption of men workes, taking occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:17283:129"/> by the word. Againe, the Phyſitions intemperancy will not make the preſcript of dyet leſſe regarded. But for our owne want of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; wee muſt know when we are ſo, it is not for any lack in the word, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough our owne default: when the tongue is in loſſe of taſte through choler, giue it neuer ſo good meate and drinkes, all is bitter; yet it is not in the meates, but in the taſte. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell doth by multiplicities of interpretation make ſom call the word in queſtion. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Diuerſity of gloſſe doth not take away the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme meaning of the Text, and certainty of knowledge in it. If twenty foure Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:17283:129"/> ſhould demurre vpon ſome caſe; though they had twelue diuers interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it doth not take away certainty in the Lawe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>this is a rotten bleat,</hi> not of Chriſts ſheep, How ſhould we knowe the mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning of the Scriptures? <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. His ſheepe heare his voyce. God hath promiſed we ſhal be all taught of him, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, the Diuell will ſteale away the word from vs, for hee is light fingred. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.19, Then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the euill one &amp; catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth &amp;c. There is an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Apoſtles, out of whoſe hearts hee did ſteale the word of Chriſts reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo plainely foretolde them. And wee ſee in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:17283:130"/> ſome remember not two ſentences, at the end of the week, not one: cares, buſineſſes, pleaſures, &amp;c. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> we muſt be armd, with remembring of Chriſts admonition,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 8 18</note> Take heede how yee heare. It is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous meddling with edge-tools: Bleſſed are thoſe that heare the word of God and keepe it. <hi>Heb.</hi> 15, To day if yee wil heare his voyce, &amp;c. The danger of not keeping the word and bringing forth fruit, is ſet forth, by the ground drinking in the ſhowers; &amp; fruitleſſe, which is neare vnto curſing. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.8. And to this purpoſe marke the fourth thing: <hi>How wee may doe that the word may be held of vs.</hi> Wee
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:17283:130"/> 
               <hi>must aboue all things keepe our hearts:</hi> for they are the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels in which the word muſt be ſtored; if the veſſell leak, or be not ſweet, the liquor runneth out, or ſmelleth of the caske: If the heart bee vnbeleeuing, giuen to luſt, couetouſneſſe, voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the word will runne out, or be ſmothred, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted. Therefore <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, Encline my heart to thy teſtimonies, and not to couetouſneſſe: theſe two cannot ſtand together. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>wee muſt labour to ſee how precious the word is.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119 103.</note> 
               <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid</hi> found it more ſweet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hony combe, more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious then golde or ſiluer: therefore hee held it ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly. I am like a bottle in
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:17283:131"/> the ſmoake; yet I forget not thy commandements.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>wee muſt cry to God, to giue vs that faithfull remembrancer:</hi> the which may call things wee knowe to our minde, in the time of our need.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.26</note> It is ſayd whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles receiued the Spirit, then they remembred &amp;c. Without the helpe of Gods ſpirit wee ſhould bee like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar,</hi> ready to die for thirſt, though the fountaine were by vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, <hi>vve must lay vppe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the word ſafe; as we coffer iewels: to which three things are neceſſarie.</hi> Firſt, muſing &amp; conſidering with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our ſelues of it. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.19, Mary kept all theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and pondred them in her heart. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:17283:131"/> of it, <hi>Deuter.</hi> 6.7, And thou ſhalt reherſe them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually vnto thy children; not that vve muſt talk light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vvith hearts vntuned, but either with hearts prepared, or elſe with a holy purpoſe, to provoke our dull hearts by the words of our mouths: for though words com from the heart, yet they helpe the grace in the heart: as appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel is firſt warmed by the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, afterwards giueth and foſtereth heat in the body: ſuch holy communication will make vs ready in the knowledge of it. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> one that will haue it ſure, muſt not only knowe it, and haue it in his memory, for if hee goe no further it vvill putrefie &amp; com to nothing;
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:17283:132"/> but muſt affect it, that vvee may ſay ſo loue I thy ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes. 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> Becauſe they receiued not the truth in loue, therefore they did not hould to it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.122, I reioiced at thy teſtimonies as if I had found great ſpoils.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Now the things to bee marked are two: Firſt, that <hi>all of vs muſt ſtrengthen our ſelues, by getting the knowledge of Gods word.</hi> The ſvvord is not more neceſſary for the ſouldier,<note place="margin">Examples.</note> then this for vs. Thus Chriſt<note place="margin">Chriſt.</note> plaied his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes with it in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. <hi>Iob</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob.</note> 23.12, Neither haue I departed from the commandements of his lips, and I haue eſteemed the words of his mouth, more
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:17283:132"/> then mine appointed food. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.11,<note place="margin">Dauid.</note> I haue hid thy promiſe in my heart, that I might not offend againſt thee. Such as haue enemies, doe not walk but hauing their ſwordes girt to them: wee cannot repell wicked ſuggeſtions, ſtrike downe our own corruptions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of the ſvvord, and knowledge of Gods pure word.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Which doth firſt let vs ſee the leudnes of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: for firſt as they giue vs a vvicker ſhield, and paper helmet, ſo they giue vs a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſvvord, an vnwritten vvord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the vvord of men, as well as of God, the mixture doth marre the metall: but
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:17283:133"/> aboue al, heerin they ſin, that they let not Chriſtians indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently haue the word of God in their mother-to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue; vſing againſt Chriſtians the like hoſtility that the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims vſed againſt Iſrael, they tooke away the ſmiths and weapons of Iſrael. And mark it: for, this taking the word from Gods people, is an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian practice. <hi>If a man ſhould tranſport our armour, and ſo diſ-furniſh the Realme,</hi> it would not ſerue the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in time of need, vvee would count him no friend to the State.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it doth <hi>conuince Chriſtians that are careleſſe of the word of GOD:</hi> or if they haue the knowledge of it,
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:17283:133"/> 
               <hi>they vſe it as our gentility wear their weapons, to ſhew the gilded pummels and veluet ſcabberds, rather then otherwiſe:</hi> ſo the word which is a ſpirituall ſword, <hi>many do diſcourſe of it for ostentation, rather then to ward off wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſuggeſtions, or hew downe their owne corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Laſtly, <hi>wee muſt bee exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to get the knowledge of the word, and hould it faſt. Pro.</hi> 2.1, My ſonne, if thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my words, and hide my commandements vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee, verſe 5, then ſhalt thou vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, &amp; find the knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. Let the vvord of God dvvell in you richly in all vviſdome, teaching &amp;
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:17283:134"/> admoniſhing one another, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. Wee ſhould euer haue this word in our harts and mouthes: it is no ſmall diſadvantage for a man to be vvithout a vveapon in the midſt of his enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, this doth teach vs, <hi>what word it is which the ſpirit of God doth accompany, and make mighty in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: it is the word of God, Eſay</hi> 49. <hi>vlt.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8, Hovv ſhall not the miniſtration of the ſpirit be much more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious? <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.22. &amp; 29, But if they had ſtood in my cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and declared my words to my people, then they ſhould haue turned them from their euill vvay. And in regard that it is thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied,
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:17283:134"/> it is heer and in <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12, called a two edged ſvvord, of ſo great efficacy, that vvee may ſee the Apoſtles, vvho beeing but fiſhermen, yet hauing this vvord in their mouthes, did caſt dovvne all the vviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the vvorld that reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted them. And vvee ſee in that Nicene Councel,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> vvhen all the Doctours could not ſilence an acute Heretick, a ſimple man vnlearned in compariſon, bringing out the ſimple teſtimony of this vvord, did ſubdue him, and convince him, ſo that hee had not ought to anſvver.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> Which ſhould teach vs, as vvee vvould haue the ſpirit effectuall vvith vs, to keepe
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:17283:135"/> to the pure vvord, theſe cleer fountaines of Iſrael; not to affect the depths of humane curioſity: for, the ſpirit blovves not in theſe voices. Euery ſound is not muſick; nor euery ſuch ſermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> And it ſhevveth people vvhat they ſhould deſire: to heare the vvord of God, by vvhich the ſpirit doth work in them; not to applaud ſtrange fire: vvhich men do through ignorance, vvhich is the mother of admiration; and through indiſcretion, vvhich maketh them they cannot diſcerne betvveene <hi>Aarons</hi> bells, betvveene the ſiluer Trumpet of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and ſuch tinkling
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:17283:135"/> Cymbals.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> Fourthly, from tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, obiections are made: Firſt, your Bibles are not ſuch as haue infallible truth, but are the labour of men, and erre heer and there: that vvhich is the vvork of man, and ſubiect to error, is not Gods vvord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 1. Our Bibles are not ſo infallible as the firſt copies vvere (for in them not onely the matter, but manner of vvriting, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vvas <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible) and are ſuch as (for matter) into vvhich may creep ſome errour; and for phraſe of ſpeech, ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from the truth of the originall. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 2. The vvord
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:17283:136"/> tranſlated, though ſubiect to error, is Gods word, and begetteth, and encreaſeth faith, not ſo farre forth as man through frailty erreth; but as he is aſſiſted through ſpeaking and tranſlating, to write the truth.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts ſay, there muſt bee infallibility in God reuealing, and the Church propounding, to begette faith: but this is falſe; for faith commeth by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word of God, from the mouth of a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Miniſter, who by all confeſſion is ſubiect to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But if we erre in ſome things, how can wee beleeue any thing? they may as wel erre in all? <hi>Anſ</hi> It
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:17283:136"/> cannot be: becauſe as God doth immediately and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly aſſiſt them, that they cannot erre at all; ſo wee knowe hee is in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with them, that they cannot altogether erre. Theſe grounds laide, it is eaſie to anſwere. Secondly, If it be obiected, the word you preach and heare, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated and read, is ſubiect to error. Gods word is not ſubiect to error, <hi>ergo,</hi> the word yee heare and reade is not Gods word. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The propoſition if generall, it is falſe: but it is particular, &amp; ſo concludes particularly; elſe it is falſe, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion falſe, <hi>Obiect.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> A word that may erre cannot beget
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:17283:137"/> faith: your word may. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The firſt is falſe, vnleſſe conceiued with limitation, thus: A word that erreth cannot beget faith, ſo farre forth as it erreth. I thought good not to propound this obiection, becauſe I would not teach men to finde a hole in their Bibles, leſt their corruption ſhould take further holde by it, then their grace would ouer come. Yet the frequent au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious practice of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, in correcting the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations which walke in our Lands, doth make it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, that the truth of this point ſhould for the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent reader bee vnfolded; who will not take offence
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:17283:137"/> at the weakeneſſe of man, but extoll the power of God; which doth put forth it ſelfe in the midſt of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fraylties.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thing, in which the particular ſtrengthning of our ſelues doth ſtand: and that is a matter of fact. The exerciſe of prayer. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer things doo preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, men clad in gliſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring furniture, from top to toe: And this doth ſhewe vnto vs the muſter of ſuch glorious ſpirituall forces.</p>
            <p>In this eighteenth verſe, and the two following, <hi>are ſet downe three things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer.</hi> Firſt, the dutie it ſelfe; Pray alwaies, with
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:17283:138"/> all manner of prayer, &amp;c. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the manner, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from a vertue that muſt accompanie it: and partly from a property of perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the obiect or parties ſet downe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally in this verſe; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly in the verſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This is the ſumme of the verſe.</p>
            <p>The dutie hath his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plification from the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of it [with all prayer] which is all the kindes of prayer, which are opened, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, I exhort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c. Firſt, <hi>deprecatiue, or prayers,</hi> that aske remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueall of euils. 2. <hi>Petitions, or wiſhes,</hi> of good things. 3. <hi>Interc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion,</hi> for others. 4.
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:17283:138"/> 
               <hi>Thankeſgiuing.</hi> Secondly, the dutie is ſet downe for cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of time [alwaies] which doth not note that wee ſhould bee daily, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly occupied in praier; but that ever and anon, in fit opportunities, we ſhould betake our ſelues to prayer. Wee haue elſe-where the ſame manner of phraſe. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.16, Reioyce alwaies, not that wee ſhould bee like <hi>Democritus</hi> alwaies laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but when occaſion is offered, ſhewe that reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; as otherwhiles, wee muſt weepe with them that weepe. The like phraſe, 2. <hi>Samu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> did alwaies eate bread at <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uids</hi> table: that is, dayly
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:17283:139"/> at the houres of eating, hee did remaine at the Kings board. Thirdly, in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: ſignifying the fountain, whence it muſt ſpring; from our ſpirits, mooued by the ſpirit of God, which is the inditer of prayer. Theſe are opened, as having in them ſome difficulty. Now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to the generall handling of this 18. verſe. Secondly, to the particular. <hi>Prayer is an opening of the heart to God, in making re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts and offering thankes tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough Chriſt.</hi> For the nature of it is nothing but a moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule in deſire and thankeſgiuing: called the lifting vp of, or the rearing vp of the ſoule.</p>
            <pb n="271" facs="tcp:17283:139"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The vſe of it is not to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, or merit. <hi>Beggers pay no debts, but confeſſe inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. Dan.</hi> 9.5, It pleadeth all guilty, and vnworthineſs: and how can hee demerit with prayer, that cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite ought hee hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Wee are leſſe then the leaſt of his mercies: as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, Pſalm.</hi> 116.12, What ſhall I giue the Lord for all his benefits vnto mee? <hi>The vſe of it may bee branched out. In regarde of God:</hi> It doth glorifie him, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging him the father of lights, the fountaine of all good wee haue and would haue. <hi>In regarde of men,</hi> the helping of them thorough loue, by being futers at the
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:17283:140"/> throne of grace for them through Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, in regard of our ſelues, the vſe is manifold: but heere thoſe vſes of prayer are moſt pertinent, which doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the warfare wee haue in hand.</hi> Firſt, <hi>it doth make vs winne the day without ſtriking a ſtroake:</hi> For it keepeth the Diuell out, that hee cannot haue leaue to throwe a dart againſt vs. <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.41, Pray that yee enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation. <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36, Pray that you may eſcape theſe things, that ſhall come to paſſe, and that you may ſtand before the Sonne of man. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>it doth get vs ſupply of ſtrength, if vvee come to the encounter.</hi> For,
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:17283:140"/> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.11. <hi>Moſes prayer</hi> was ſtronger then <hi>Iehoſuahs</hi> ſword. Pray, and the peace of God ſhall like a watch-tower k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epe your hearts. Looke how Captaines figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting abroad for their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſend their Letters, and ſo haue men, munition, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, mony, &amp;c. So pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the meſſenger of a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, and fetcheth euery thing from God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Prayer doth ſtrengthen vs in faith and hope.</hi> For, look as if we commune often, and familiarly with a man, wee haue more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence towardes him: ſo If wee by often prayer, ſpeak with our God, it doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolden vs, and breed more
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:17283:141"/> liberty and confidence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, then if we were eſtranged. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. <hi>Prayer getteth all our other armour fitted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs;</hi> we being not able to buckle it on, further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heauenly father doth helpe vs on with it.</p>
            <p>Now for the third thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>How the Diuell doth labour to weaken vs in the performance of this dutie.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>1</label> Firſt, from this, that prayers doe not alwaies ſpeed, and therefore are in vaine. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.8, <hi>For this I beſought the Lord thrice;</hi> yet hee miſſed of that hee ſought: much more, we in temporal things. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That is not in vaine, which doth n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t alwaies get the thing wee would haue: about which wee muſt
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:17283:141"/> learne three things.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that prayer often doth obtaine what wee would: as <hi>Moſes,</hi> for victory, and had it: <hi>Hanna</hi> for a ſonne, and had him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, when it doth not obtaine the things themſelues, it gets ſomthing that may be worth our ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king: as, though it doth not quite remooue evils, yet it preuaileth ſo farre, as to haue mercy mingled with iudgement; our evills aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaged. Though wee get not the things wee wiſh, it getteth ſome grace proportionable: as in <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. My grace is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for thee. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> though it get not deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, <hi>ad voluntatem,</hi> yet
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:17283:142"/> it alwaies procures iſſue <hi>ad ſalutem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>from this that praiers are needleſſe. Eſay</hi> 65.24, Yea, before they call I vvill anſvver, and vvhileſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſpeak I vvill heare. And <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.24. Henceforth you ſhall ask mee nothing. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The later is but a doubt from the phraſe of ſpeech: for, asking there is queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as they had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; vvhich they ſhould not need to doo vvhen they had the ſpirit to lead them into all truth: for the other it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovveth not, God is ready to forgiue vs, therfore we need not aske: for although it is not needful to ſtirre vp mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in him vvho is the bovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:17283:142"/> of mercy, or to informe him vvho is the ſearcher of hearts, yet they are neceſſary as meanes vvhich God vvill haue vſed, that vvee may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things vvhich hee of free mercy giueth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25 21, <hi>Iſaac</hi> knevv he ſhould haue ſeed before, yet he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. <hi>Elias</hi> knevv, and had told <hi>Ahab,</hi> God would certainly giue raine: yet both prayed, and they are meanes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs holily to enioy the things receiued. The crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is ſanctified by prayer: for things receiued by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er encreaſe our loue to God, our thankefulnes. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116, What ſhal I render vnto the Lord, for all his benefites: maketh vs ready to part
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:17283:143"/> with them for Gods glory.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>from our vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe. God heareth not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Iohn</hi> 9.31. And alſo if I regard wickedneſſe, the Lord will not heare mee. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> There are repenting and vnrepenting ſinners: the later kinde of ſinners, nay, their very prayers are an abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when they loue to liue in ſome ſin, and hate to bee reformed. The other God heareth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, <hi>God heareth not ſuch as doubt of his mercy. Iam.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> There is a <hi>raigning vnbeleefe;</hi> and there is a <hi>doubting, and vnbeliefe</hi> which is a weakneſſe left in the Saints, for their exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe. The firſt is in heathens
<pb n="279" facs="tcp:17283:143"/> and vnbeleeuers: the later, which is a doubting which is in a ſoule that would be rid of it, and prayer by faith fights againſt it, doth not hinder vs from being heard. <hi>Marke</hi> 9.22, But if thou canſt doe any thing help vs. <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.31, Oh thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>5</label> Fiftly, <hi>From our long aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and not receiuing. It is in vaine for him to pray that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and receiueth not. Anſ.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, we muſt examine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our continuing in ſom luſt, doe not hinder the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our prayer. <hi>Iames</hi> 4.3, Yee aske and haue not, becauſe ye aske amiſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Wee muſt knowe that God
<pb n="280" facs="tcp:17283:144"/> doth deferre vs, to try how we will perſeuere in prayer; as a friend when hee mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to doe this or that, doth detract it at the firſt, to ſee if the other will impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune him. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, that we may knowe the worth of things, and haue our ioy doubled in receiuing them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, It is a token God will giue vs more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, the longer hee doth holde vs in requeſt: the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one openeth any thing, it is a token vvee meane to put the more in. It is not in vaine therefore to aske, though wee be not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly anſwered; ſeeing God doth on ſo good occaſions, delay vs in our ſuits. And
<pb n="281" facs="tcp:17283:144"/> let vs be ſure of this, that he that bottleth vp our teares, files vp our prayers, putting them on record before him. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.16, Then ſpake they that feared the Lord, euery one to his neighbour, &amp; the Lord harkened and heard it, and a booke of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought vpon his name. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>6</label> Sixtly, <hi>the Diuell by tempting vs to ſinne, and diſtempering of vs in the courſe of prayer.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7, Likewiſe, yee husbands dwell with your wiues, as men of knowledge, giving honour vnto the woman, as vnto the weaker veſſell, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as they which are heirs
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:17283:145"/> together of the grace of life, that your prayers be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted. For, when the conſcience is defiled, wee are ſo pricked in the foote, that we cannot goe to God in prayer; and are not able comfortably to diſcharge it: wee either neglect them, or profane Gods name, in ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing vpon them: we muſt therefore take heede of ſin, as wee would with comfort return to prayers. But here is a queſtion. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>I haue beene o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertaken with infirmitie, the time of prayer draweth on, what ſhall I doe? Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Firſt, thou muſt not neglect it, for this is to heap one ſinne vpon another. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.24, Leaue there thine offering
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:17283:145"/> before the Altar, and goe thy way, firſt be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, thou muſt not when thou haſt offended God ruſh boldly on him. <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.10, They worſhipped e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man a farre off, in the door of his tent: but <hi>Num.</hi> 12.14. There is a worthy example, If a mans parent ſhould be ſo offended, as to ſpet on him; durſt hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him for ſeauen dayes? And ſhall wee bee ſo bolde, hauing offended the father of ſpirits, preſently to come into his ſight? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third place, a man muſt gather himſelfe together, &amp; let his heart ſmite him in
<pb n="284" facs="tcp:17283:146"/> that hee hath done, the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to think what ſtreights hee hath brought himſelfe vnto, either in neglecting his dutie, or profaning the name of his God. If the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie bee at hand (as the man and wife) let there bee mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall confeſſion; if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, let there be a purpoſe of it: and hauing this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and being in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure touched, though no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo well as wee wiſh, and were meet; wee may come to God, and he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept vs, and heale vs. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.19, And his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and how God was intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of him, &amp;c. Seauenthly, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>The Diuell will labour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vs, and breake vs off in
<pb n="285" facs="tcp:17283:146"/> this dutie, by diſtractions; this thing, and that, calling vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> by difficulties in the while of prayer: ſuch miſts of darkneſſe, ſuch ſwarmes of wandering idle thoghts, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming before our mindes, that wee are much diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Wee muſt be reſolute againſt diſtractions. Firſt ſeeeke the kingdom of God, &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. If wee promiſe at this or that houre, to meet a man when the Clock ſmiteth, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer wee are with, wee craue pardon; wee are to goe. <hi>Make not more bolde with God then you would with man.</hi> For the ſecond we muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire whether letting looſe our hearts all day, doe not
<pb n="286" facs="tcp:17283:147"/> cauſe this vnfitneſs at night: and if it be ſo, we muſt help the matter with watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, wee muſt knowe that the Saints haue felt both theſe things, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wandrings. For there is a double wandering of the minde: one is of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe and contempt, ſuch as is in many in the Church, that pray, and their mindes are a wool-gathering; they ſay Amen, but know not to what. There is another wandering of the minde, which is through infirmity: it being felt, is grieuous to vs, though we cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome it. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this is a rule, We muſt not ceaſe to doe any commandment
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:17283:147"/> becauſe of our imperfection in dooing it. And to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then vs euery vvay, <hi>Let vs come to the fourth conſideration, how to ſtrengthen our ſelues, that we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly cary forth this duty:</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to conſider that this is a commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and that neceſſity doth lie vpon vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the promiſe of God, Ask and yee ſhall haue, ſeek, &amp;c. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to muſe often on the ſtile of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.2, Hee is a God that heareth praier: looke the vvhole Pſalme. If Princes will not loſe any part of their Royall Title, God vvill maintaine his.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, to conſider, it is our ſelues that gaine by
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:17283:148"/> praier: and if we lay it down, wee ſhall haue the loſſe of it. <hi>Iob</hi> 35.7, If thou be righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, what giueſt thou vnto him, &amp;c? Yea, we muſt be ſo far from beeing offended at Gods not anſwering at our want of comfort and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, that wee muſt hould euen this, ſuch a prerogatiue as wee are vnworthy of. 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.14, What am I or my people that we ſhould offer thus? what are we that wee ſhould ſpeake to God, or haue acceſſe to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Maieſty?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, to conſider againſt all wants, that wee are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, according to that vvee haue when there is a ready minde, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. Hee
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:17283:148"/> ſpares vs as a father doth his children, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. They will heare with delight the liſping and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mering voice of their children: yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſoule is ſicke, the ſeruice is twice welcome. If a ſicke childe reach vs vp a thing, wee count it more then to ſend another of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious arrands.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, from all wants and diſcouragements, labour to ſee that thou canſt not pray, if God by his ſpirit help thee not: the more thou comeſt to bee poore in ſpirit, the more freedom and ſtrength thou ſhalt haue in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thy duty.</p>
            <p>Now thus we ſee in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that <hi>Chriſtians muſt by
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:17283:149"/> this exerciſe of prayer ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then themſelues.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Euery where wee haue precepts, Call on mee in the time of trouble, &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15. And prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: <hi>Dauid, Aſa, Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat, Hezechiah,</hi> when the armies of the Heathen did aſſaile them, by prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt them. This is the refuge of the Saints in all troubles. The Name of the Lord is a tower of defence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.10. This is that iuſt mans practice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. the whole Pſalme.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Which doth rebuke ſuch Chriſtians as vſe not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to prayer. It is with vs as in the time of <hi>Eſay.</hi> 60.7, And there is none that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vpon thy name, neither
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:17283:149"/> that ſtirreth vp himſelfe to take hould on thee. And as with the Diſciples, <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.24, Hitherto haue yee asked nothing in my Name. We haue all things ſo caſt vpon vs, that wee vſe not prayer: but take heed; for the Lord will draw back his hand, and rather ſtrip you that are his owne of all, then leeſe his honour. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5, I will go and returne to my place, till they acknowledge their fault, and ſeeke mee: in their affliction they will ſeeke mee diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If wee will not ſeek him, hee will make vs cry after him: therfore do not (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer condition you are of) ſhift it off. Wiues thinke the husband muſt doo it: but his
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:17283:150"/> neglect will not diſcharge thy duty. Seruants thinke if their maſters vſe none, they are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to none. <hi>Why ſhould we need motiues to this?</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If we might bee familiarly admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Kings preſence, vvee would eaſily accept it: in faithfull praier thou maiſt commune with God. Again, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> how worthy are we to miſſe good things, that will not open our mouths for them? <hi>Spare to ſpeak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (vvee ſay) <hi>and ſpare to ſpeed.</hi> When GOD biddeth vs aske and haue, hovv vnthankfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthy vvretches are vvee, that neglect ſuch kindneſſe, and vvill not prooue him that is ſo gracious? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Againe, there is no duty ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:17283:150"/> to God: for that prayer is to grace, as povvning is to ſvveete ſpices; it maketh grace, as faith, reuerence, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty of ſpirit, thankfulnes, &amp;c. caſt a fragrant ſmell, as vvhich (indeed) is nothing but the chafing of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, vvee ſee, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>day by day, when it ſhall bee most fitting our condition and occaſion, wee muſt returne to this duty,</hi> Pray alvvaies. That vvee are ſaid to doo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, vvhich vvee are ſaid to doo at fit times daily, as <hi>Numb.</hi> 28, That vvas a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſacrifice vvhich vvas daily offred, morning and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening only. <hi>And that we are daily to take vp this exerciſe, it appeareth by</hi> Dauid, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 55.
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:17283:151"/> 17, Euening and morning and noone, vvill I pray and make a noiſe, and hee ſhall heare my voice. <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.10, He kneeled vpon his knees three times a day, and praid and praiſed his God, as hee had done aforetimes. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> by Chriſts inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, vvho vvould haue vs begge euery day the things that belong to this tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> much more to the ſpirituall. And <hi>by many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> as firſt our decay of grace vvhen it is not renevved, or ſundry vvants and nevv ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of euil vvhich dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhevv themſelues, before not diſcouered, vvhich muſt bee ſupplied by praier; as the decay daily of bodily ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:17283:151"/> by ſuſtentation. Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the daily malice of Satan a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of daily prayer, it is as a hedge to vs. When we haue brought our ſelues to this cuſtome (it beeing vvith the ſoule as vvith the body) it vvill not goe quietly vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that to vvhich it is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Firſt therefore from the right vnderſtanding this phraſe, vve ſee it doth not enioyne vs thoſe canonicall hovvers: for beſides that their inſtitution vvas not knovven in the Apoſtles time, this precept tieth all Chriſtians; vvhereas their hovvers of praier bind their clergie onely, vvho of office
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:17283:152"/> are to pray, and there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that way, would haue theſe things marked; that wee doe not deny that the Church hath liberty to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houres, with caution of edification. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But the firſt erre in this, that they make lawes for all times, of ſome example, which particular men did freely vpon ſome occaſion extraordinay. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. That they multiply their <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria's,</hi> and houres abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, aboue that the Church of God can attend vnto, yea contrary to Gods inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who hath, that we might keepe his worſhippe on the Sabbath, giuen vs ſix dayes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That they make them publike prayers of the Chur.
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:17283:152"/> which are performed by the Clergie; wheras the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie are not the Church, but the miniſters with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to whom it is miniſtred.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, this doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince many, who think that time loſt that is deuoted to prayer, who thinke it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to pray at Church; as if Gods publike ſeruice did iuſtle forth the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate. Many, who by fittes ſometime will pray, leauing off another while. Many, who though they pray in euening with their houſes, yet in the morning euery man muſt bee for him ſelfe, and God for them all: but wee muſt pray alwaies, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and morning, day by
<pb n="298" facs="tcp:17283:153"/> day; it is moſt requiſite that wee Chriſtians may offer vp a continuall ſpirituall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to our God, though e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one cannot in the like meaſure performe theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for the circumſtances of callings, and conditions of liues, do make them differ.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 3. In the ſpirit. Which doth teach vs, <hi>that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man of our hearts, must chiefly be occupied in prayer.</hi> In all our ſeruice, wee ſhould ſay, as <hi>Ro.</hi> 1.9. That we ſerue God in our ſpirites, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie in prayer; it being not the warbling of words, but the yearning, and pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the heart after God, and the things of our peace. Such was Chriſts prayer, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.7, which in the dayes
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:17283:153"/> of his fleſh did offer vp prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſtrong cries vnto him, &amp;c. From his ſoule they came: for they were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred vp with lowd cries, and many tears. And the ardent deſire, is the thing which God heareth, though there be no voyce annexed; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 14:15, Why cryeſt thou vnto me? 2. The prayer outward of the lippes, without the requeſt of the heart, is abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable in his ſight. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 15.8, Curſed is hee that draweth neere with his lips, but his heart is farre from mee. <hi>The ſpirit is the riſe of true prayer: if it proceed not thence, it is an empty ring which God regardeth not.</hi> And
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:17283:154"/> this maketh prayer labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, becauſe the ſpirit is to trauaile in it: and the Saints in this regarde, can endure better to heare an houre, then pray a quarter; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the world, they think the out warde repeating of words with a generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, to ſuffice. This Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery is naturall, they cry for praying, rather then prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reprehenſion. </seg>
               </label> It doth ſerue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince ſuch prayers as are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vain babbling, &amp; wordes without ſpirit: as with many, the minde is running on twenty things, while the bodie boweth to prayer. Yea, it doth check the indeuotion, and want of ſpirit, that doth creep vpon
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:17283:154"/> vs, that are the Lords. And let vs take heed: for a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe prayer, if it come not from meer feebleneſs, which is accompanied with an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectneſſe of heart, but as it doth the moſt times from a ſpirit of ſloath ioyned with preſumption; <hi>If we from theſe grounds ſhuffle vp our prayers without pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r &amp; life,</hi> God wil certainely puniſh our profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his name, with let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vs fall into ſome ſinne, which ſhall awaken vs with ſmart enough.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, this doth teach vs that we muſt ſtirre vp our ſpirits in the action of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, vſe contention, &amp; ſhake off ſuch chilneſſe, as wil run through vs, crying to him
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:17283:155"/> that is the quickning ſpirit, not being quiet till wee get ſome warmth into our ſpirites: and theſe bee the winged prayers, that flie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the viſible heauens; theſe bee the prayers of ſmoake, in which the Church aſcendeth to God, out of this world, a barren wilderneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> Fourthly, watching ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Whence marke, <hi>that as vvee muſt pray, ſo vvee muſt vſe watchfulneſſe for furtherance of prayer:</hi> Not that wee ſhould ſit vp late, as in <hi>Nocturnes;</hi> or wake before day, as in morning <hi>Mattens:</hi> But vvee muſt all day long haue a wakening ſoule, that carrieth the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="303" facs="tcp:17283:155"/> of prayer in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance. Watch &amp; pray, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.2, Continue in praier, and watch in the ſame with thankeſgiuing. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7, The end of all things is at hand, be yee therefore ſober and watching in prayer. Where we may ſee, it is the mindes waking, which is principally meant, though this wil keep the bodie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drowſineſſe, in performing the exerciſe. The primitiue Chriſtians, this is recorded of them; that they did eate their meate, as remembring they were to call on God, by the night ſeaſon. <hi>More par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, there muſt be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe brfore prayer.</hi> 2. <hi>In it.</hi> 3. <hi>After it.</hi> Now our watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:17283:156"/> before, ſtands in preuenting the impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in marking that in the courſe of the day, which may fit vs for prayer. Firſt, this watchfulnes will make a man ſo caſt, and make ſuch riddance of buſineſſe, that he may not haue hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces when he ſhall goe to his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. God prefixeth a <hi>Meme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> before the Sabbath; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that if one doe not lift vp his minde to it, and in the ſix dayes diſpatch his buſineſſe, hee cannot keepe it when it commeth: ſo there is a mindfulneſſe to be had of him that will not this way be encombred with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions. Secondly, Wee muſt watchfully keepe our
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:17283:156"/> ſelues from ſinne: Let him that calleth on the name of Lord, depart from iniquitie. <hi>For if we be in the day time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent to our luſts, it will be a dampe to our prayers: and when wee yeeld to ſinne, it is a token our Watch is downe;</hi> vve think not of prayer. For if wee meant to make ſuite to a man at night, wee would be watchfull in the day, not to loſe his fauour, by giuing him offence, leſt hee ſhould refuſe vs in our requeſt. 2. We muſt obſerue our wants in the day time; as, how prone we are to runne into worldly mindedneſſe, in wrath, in voluptuouſnes, in fooliſh and vnfruitfull ſpeaking, and therefore,
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:17283:157"/> what need wee haue to cry, Lord, keepe thou the door of our lips. Again, we muſt labour, as to haue a ſenſe of wants, ſo to haue a feeling of the good things God giueth, of the euils hee keepeth from vs: for vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the one wee cannot bee poore in ſpirit, nor beg vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly; without the other wee cannot be truely thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and offer vp our praiſe hartily.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now we muſt watch in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er against indeuotion and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Eſay</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth 64.7, And there is none that calleth on thy Name, neither that ſtirreth vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to take hould on thee. <hi>After praier wee muſt marke,</hi>
               <pb n="307" facs="tcp:17283:157"/> how God hath anſwered vs in this or that wee haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.3, Early in the morning will direct my praier vnto thee, and vvill wait, ſtand as in a watch-tower, and ſee how the Lord will deale with mee, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member mee in my requeſts. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.5, I haue waited on the Lord, my ſoule hath waited, and I haue truſted in his word, ver. 6.7.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reprehen∣ſion. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>This doctrine checketh ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; ſuch, as when their Watch hath beene downe, ruſh vpon praier,</hi> euen from pots to praier: when they haue ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped &amp; giuen thanks, though they haue let their hearts looſe, eat, drunke without fear, ſobriety, profaned their
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:17283:158"/> mouthes with light vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſpeech, yet then before parting of friends, call for a praier. But though they may after a feaſt go to praier, who eat and drinke before the Lord, as <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. after ſhee had exceeded with a double portion, went and praied deuoutly; yet you that haue let fal your Watch in feaſting, you profane Gods Name when you call for a praier: and many are ſo farre from remembring themſelues all day, that they cannot keep their eyes open while they are a-praying; they are ſo affected, as if it would caſt them into an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue to bee kept awhile in praier. This want of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:17283:158"/> is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon euill, and doth vs great hurt. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs ſuch poore Orators, that when we come to God, wee are barren of praiſe and requeſt, becauſe we doe not obſerue in the day matter for this purpoſe: this, though we knowe it not, doth make vs complaine of ſuch miſts, rouing thoughts, indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe wee walke all day long forgetfull. If one ſhould eat codlings, gooſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, peaſe, would you wonder if at night hee were wrung in his belly? would you not bid him mend his diet if hee meant to ſee it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe? ſo, when wee let our hearts looſe all day, feed vpon earthly vanity, how
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:17283:159"/> ſhould they bee heauenly-minded on a ſudden, vvhen bed-time calleth on vs to praier?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exhortati∣on. </seg>
               </label> Let vs ſtir vp our ſelues to keepe this watch, that wee may ſee, and walke in the ſtrength of our praiers. <hi>If one be to make an oration in the ſchooles,</hi> hee will not venture <hi>ex tempore:</hi> how much more ſhould wee meditate on the orations wee are to make be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord? So <hi>if we ſhould deuiſe any thing by way of petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> would wee not wait how it is receiued? what is ſaid to it? would we giue vp our petition, and careleſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, never thinking on it? how much more ſhould we wait to ſee what will becom
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:17283:159"/> of our requeſts to GOD?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With perſeuerance.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> VVhence marke, that <hi>wee muſt hold out in our daily courſe of praier.</hi> VVhat if God delay, we muſt not giue in, but like <hi>Iacob,</hi> not let God goe till hee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs the bleſſing; and like thoſe remembrancers of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Eſay,</hi> giue him no reſt till hee accompliſh our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. This, our Sauiour by two parables calleth vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; one, of a friend impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuning his friend in the night, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.5.6.7.8. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of a widow dealing with the vnrighteous Iudge <hi>Luke</hi> 18.2.3.4.5. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance is a thing ſo loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that therefore God doth delay, to ſee how we vvill be
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:17283:160"/> inſtant, and importunate vvith him. For he doth not ſeeme to reiect prayers that hee doth not heare, &amp; grant them,: nay, as ſeed which is the longeſt couered riſeth the firſt with moſt increaſe: ſo doe thoſe prayers which God ſeemeth to bury in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulnes a long time, if we perſeuere, they ſhall ſpring out vvith the greateſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Inſtruction </seg>
               </label> VVherefore vvee muſt ſtirre vp our ſelues, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our feeble knees, erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our fainting hearts, we muſt not let delay beate vs out. Shall we ſtint God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to heare vs? Let hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites ſay, <hi>Eſay</hi> 58, VVee haue faſted, and thou regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not. Are we better then
<pb n="313" facs="tcp:17283:160"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> vvho praied thrice, yet vvas glad to reſt in this, that Gods grace vvas ſufficient? better then thoſe that haue ſaid, Hovv long? Haue not vve, vvhen God hath called and knocked, often neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to anſvver? Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe things: and though God ſeem to turne a deafe eare tovvards vs, let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our praiers with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
